<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Antipharmacum Saluberrimum; or, A serious &amp; seasonable caveat to all the saints in this hour of temptation. Wherein their present dangers are detected, and their present duties vigorously urged</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75477</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229361</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900193</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900193</idno>
            <idno type="VID">136315</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75477)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 136315)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2542:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Antipharmacum Saluberrimum; or, A serious &amp; seasonable caveat to all the saints in this hour of temptation. Wherein their present dangers are detected, and their present duties vigorously urged</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Life skills --  Handbooks, manuals, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:136315:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Antipharmacum Saluberrimum;</hi> OR, A SERIOUS &amp; SEASONABLE CAVEAT To all the SAINTS In this hour of Temptation. Wherein their preſent Dangers are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, and their preſent Duties vigorouſly urged.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 35.3, 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Strengthen ye the weak hands, and confirm the feeble knees: Say to them that are of a fearful heart, Be ſtrong, fear not; behold your God will come with vengeance, even God with a recompence, he will come and ſave you.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 16.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Behold I come as a thief, bleſſed is he that watcheth, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Garments, leſt he walk naked, and they ſee his ſhame.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Quo quis ſanctior, eo promptior novellis contra ire.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Virenen.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Hominibus placere non licet, ubi voluntas hominum, non capit Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini voluntatem.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:136315:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:136315:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS God hath ſtretched out the <hi>Expanſum</hi> or Firmament of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, over the natural World, ſo hath he ſtretcht out his Word over the rational World; and as in that he hath placed the Stars and Luminaries, to enlighten the Earth, and to be for <hi>Signs,</hi> and for Seaſons, <hi>Gen. 1.14.</hi> So hath he placed a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation of Scriptures in this alſo, by which they that are skilful in the Word of Righteouſneſs, may diſcern very much of the Deſigns and Iſſues of thoſe rouling and amazing Providences that are over our heads.</p>
            <p>And doubtleſs, nothing more ſettles and ſupports the hearts of Saints, under terrible and tempeſtuous Providences, then to view them in their reference and relation to the World: for of theſe we may ſay as <hi>David</hi> doth, <hi>Pſal, 148.8.</hi> of the ſtormy Winds, that they fulfill his Word, and are the undoubted accompliſhments of its Predictions, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies.</p>
            <p>Now to thoſe that heedfully obſerve the Scripture-Prophecies, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the ruine and deſtruction of Antichriſt, it cannot but appear that their accompliſhment is nigh, and that glorious Deſign come even to the birth.<note n="*" place="margin">Confundetur omne jus, &amp; leges interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt, non fides in homnibus, non pax, non pudor, neque ſecuritas, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> regimen; et hujus. confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis, haec erit cauſa, quod Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum nomen quo nune regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar orbis, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terra tolletur. <hi>Lactan. p. 576.</hi>
               </note> But then, as the darkeſt part of the night is that which immediately precedes the dawning of the day, ſo before the Vial of the Lord's Indignation be poured out upon the Throne of the Beaſt, it will be a time of trouble to the Saints, ſuch as never was ſince man was upon the Earth, <hi>Dan. 12.1.</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">It is obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that <hi>Rome</hi> in this Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, bears the name of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon.</hi> in reſpect of the miſery and bondage exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed upon Gods People by it; by which alſo, is not obſcurely hinted, the time and manner of their deliverance from it; for both from the one, and the other, were the Jews delivered, when reduced to the greateſt extremity, See <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.9. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Rev. 11.7, 8.</hi> The Witneſſes of Jeſus muſt firſt be ſlain, and their dead bodies for a time, lye in the ſtreets of the great City: And as Naturaliſts obſerve, that a Beaſt never bites more furiouſly, and deadly, then when dying; even ſo it is with this Beaſt alſo; which hath Iron teeth, and is terrible above all that were before it, <hi>Dan. 7.7.</hi> and when the ſtrong God ariſeth to judge Babylon, She ſhall be found quite drunk with the Blood of the Saints, and Martyrs of Jeſus, <hi>Rev. 17.6.</hi> So that we, whoſe lots are fallen into ſuch a day as this, wherein the fierceſt rage of the laſt &amp; moſt furious of all the Beaſts, is falling in a dreadful ſtorm upon all the reformed Churches of Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:136315:3"/>had need of a more than ordinary degree of Faith and Patience, to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh us in the Truth, and inable us to bear a glorious Teſtimony for the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>If any man's heart now ſhall fail him, and to avoid the fury of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, ſhall baſely betray the Truth, and forſake the Camp of Chriſt, and receive the mark of the Beaſt, though not in his forehead, yet in his hand, by a pollitick and ſecret Compliance with his Worſhip, that man is adjudged by the dreadful Sentence of the great God, to drink the Cup of his pure and unmixed Wrath and Indignation, <hi>Rev. 14.10.</hi> even ſuch as the Devils and damned drink: For we may ſay of that wrath, which is ordinarily poured out upon ſinners in this life, as they ſay of darkneſs, <hi>Non dantur pure tenebre;</hi> there is no pure or perfect darkneſs here; ſo neither is there any pure unmixed wrath here, it hath in this life an allay of ſparing mercy in it; but this is pure.</p>
            <p>To prevent this ſad iſſue, and preſerve thee from this terrible Wrath of the Lamb, are the following Counſels and Cautions deſigned and intended: And Oh, that they might be bleſſed to eſtabliſh the ſliding feet of tempted Saints; For I cannot without trembling obſerve, how many forward Profeſſors begin to give ground already, and fall into a Compliance with Antichriſtian Abominations; ſurely this is the worſt time that ever they could have choſen for it, now that the Day of Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is in the heart of Chriſt againſt Her, and the year of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed even come; his Righteouſneſs ſo night at hand, and his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation ready to be revealed.</p>
            <p>I ſhall detain thee no longer, but intreat thee to weigh theſe things, brought to thy hand by providence, and with the ſpirit of love, to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the weakneſſes of the Author, who is ſenſible of his own infirmities, and continual need of divine Aſſiſtance, to enable him to ſtand; And to that end earneſtly begs a remembrance in thy Prayers, when thy heart is moſt<note n="*" place="margin">Dulce cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercium, ſed breve memen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, cum talis fueris, memen to mei. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </note> warmed, enlarged, and raiſed in communion with thy God.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:136315:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Antipharmarum Saluberrimum.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Chriſtians,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHen our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">His bowels yerned.</note> the great Shepheard of the Sheep, beheld the multitude, he had<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Bowels are a metaphor, to ſignifie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.78.</note> 
               <hi>Compaſſion</hi> on them, becauſe they <hi>fainted,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. quite ſpent, ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and fallen down.</note> and were as Sheep having no Shepherd, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.36.</p>
            <p>After the pattern of thoſe tender Bowels of Chriſt, the chief Shepherd, do the Bowels of Compaſſion infuſed by him into his Miniſters, the under Shepherds, work and move towards the Flock, in like caſes &amp; exigencies. <hi>God is my record</hi> (ſaith that great Apoſtle) how greatly I long after you all<note n="*" place="margin">[In] <hi>put for</hi> [inſtar,]</note> 
               <hi>[In]</hi> or after the manner, of <hi>the Bowels of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 1.8.</p>
            <p>And truly, conſidering the deep diſtreſſes, and languiſhing conditions, to which many thouſands of the Lord's Flock are at this day expoſed, how many among you are wandering from Mountain to Hill, ſeeking Paſture, but finding none; and like thoſe Troops of <hi>Tema, Job</hi> 6.19. return aſhamed, and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, from thoſe places where you were wont to be refreſhed, enlarged, quickned: And how your pretended Shepherds have taken to themſelves the<note n="†" place="margin">forcipes, &amp; mulc tra,</note> Inſtruments of a fooliſh Shepherd, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you with force, and rigor, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.4. <hi>not ſparing the Flock,</hi> it makes my heart melt within me, and my compaſſions for you flow together.</p>
            <p>And further, apprehending what a deep and deſperate deſign your adverſary the Devil hath upon you in this hour of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to overthrow your Faith, quench your Love, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the very Foundation of your Profeſſion; and what ſingular and extraordinary advantages he hath now upon you, engaging you ſingly and apart; your faithful Teachers being removed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to corners, your Societies broken, dangers threatning on every ſide, carnal neighours and relations, by perſwaſions, examples, and dangerous inſinuations digging about and looſing your roots, and ſo preparing for your utter ſubverſion, by the next guſt of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation: I thought it high time to come in to your aſſiſtance and relief, with a Word of Counſel and Support, though I venture for you, as <hi>Davids</hi> Worthies did, to bring him the Waters of the Well of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> through the Hoſt of the Philiſtines.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:136315:4"/>
            <p>And may <hi>I</hi> but preſerve the peace of mine own conſcience, by diſcharging faithfully a duty to which it impels me, and have the bleſſing of ſome poor ſoul ready to periſh, come upon me, I ſhall little regard the pains or hazard of this enterprize for you.</p>
            <p>The plain deſign of theſe few ſheets, is to countermine the Enemy of your ſouls in his preſent grand Deſigns againſt you; either in point of ſtability, by unſetling you; or of duty, by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighting you; or of comfort, by diſcouraging you.</p>
            <p>To prevent the ſucceſs of the Tempter, in all, or either of theſe, I ſhall offer you my beſt aſſiſtance, under theſe eight enſuing Heads of Advice and Counſel; beſeeching you, by all the dear regard you have to the dreadful &amp; glorious Name of God, which is called upon you, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.10, 11. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. or to your own precious and immortal Souls, whoſe eternal happineſs is not a little engaged in theſe things, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.33. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.9. or to the comfort and encouragement of your ſuffering and afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Miniſters, and Brethren abroad, a great part of whoſe joy (yea life) lies at your mercy, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.5. and is as it were, bound up in your ſtability; that you will heedfully obſerve and embrace theſe Admonitions, according to the weight and evidence that is in them, and let not any fleſhly intereſt in the world, carry you againſt the convictions that may hereby be left upon your conſciences.</p>
            <p>And the firſt Advice or Counſel is this.</p>
            <div n="1" type="counsel">
               <head>COUNSEL. <hi>I.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cleave faſt to Chriſt, and the Profeſſion you have formerly made of him, what aſpect ſoever the times have upon you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pſal. 44.18, 19, 20, 21. <hi>Our heart is not turned back, neither have our ſteps declined from thy Way, though thou haſt ſore broken us in the place of Dragons, and covered us with the ſhadow of death. If we have forgotten the Name of the Lord, or ſtretch'd out our hands to a ſtrange god, ſhall not God ſearch out this? for he knoweth the ſecrets of the heart.</hi> Hence thoſe new Converts, who were turned to the Lord in a time of great temptation and perſecution, were ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly perſwaded, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.23. <hi>That with purpoſe of heart they would cleave unto the Lord; (i. e.)</hi> as they had made a good choice, ſo now, to ſtick to their choice, and not repent of it, whatever afterward they ſhould meet with. Oh take heed, leſt after you have lifted up your <hi>hand</hi> to God, you ſhould lift up your <hi>heel</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:136315:4"/>againſt him. Though the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 29.16</note> Hypocrite will not pray alwayes, yet the<note n="†" place="margin">Dan. <hi>6.10.</hi> Omnia de me preſumes, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fugam, qui odium et impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum totius or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ſuſtinui. <hi>Luther.</hi>
                  </note> upright Soul abhors to flinch from his duty, let come on him what will. It is now <hi>Autumn</hi> with many flouriſhing Profeſſors, but if thou be a tree planted by the River ſide, thy leaf ſhall not wither, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. You look for happineſs as long as God is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and be ſure God looks for holineſs, as long as you be on Earth. What duty is more importunately urged upon you by every part of the Goſpel, than Stability? The Preceptive part peremptorily requires it. See <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.11. theſe be commands flowing from Soveraignty, cloathed with the higheſt Authority. The Minatory part urges it; See <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.33. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. and theſe dreadful threats are diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the ſoul, and levelled at the very breaſt of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. The Promiſſory part marvellouſly encourages to it, a ſweet voice ſeems to come down from Heaven in theſe Promiſes, ſaying, <hi>Good ſouls hold faſt, if ever you hope to poſſeſs the Glory that is here, hold faſt, Gal.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.12, 21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7.</p>
               <p>Now, leſt all this ſhould leave but a floating and ineffectual conviction upon you, give me leave to follow it a little farther, and endeavour to work it in by a few warming Conſiderations upon your hearts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Conſider, God hath hanged the whole weight of Eternal Happineſs upon this Wyer; ſo that the deepeſt, deareſt, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting intereſt of thy ſoul, is bound up in thy Perſeverance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.14. and if ſo, methinks this ſhould make thee cling faſt, deſpiſe dangers; face the ſtorm, and make a ſtand for Chriſt, let come on thee what will: for conſider ſoul, what compariſon betwixt a moment ſuffering, and this Eternal Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16, 17, 18. Oh that vaſt Eternity! that amazing Word! which none but He that was from Eternity, and is to Eternity, comprehenſively underſtands: when a ſoul is ſwallowed up in it, yea, or when it ſits in a dying hour trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, upon the brink of it, how are its apprehenſions of preſent things altered!</p>
               <p n="2">2. Confider how conſtant &amp; faithful Jeſus Chriſt was to thee, when he conflicted in the dayes of his fleſh, with ſufferings, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and difficulties infinitely beyond thine; and what a motive that ſhould be, to perſwade thee to a bold and conſtant owning of him in this day of thy tryal? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.12, 13, 14. <hi>Fight the good Fight of Faith, lay hold on eternal Life, whereunto thou art al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo called, and haſt profeſſed a good Profeſſion before many witneſſes. I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:136315:5"/>give thee charge in the ſight of God, who quickneth all things, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Jeſus Chriſt, who before Pontius-Pilate witneſſed a good Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that thou keep this Commandment without ſpot.</hi> He flincht not when the Terrours of Death and Hell beſet him round: He was faithful to the truſt committed to him, till death beat the laſt breath out of his breaſt. If thou now ſtart from him, may not he ſay to thee, as that <hi>Roman</hi> Souldier ſaid to his General, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed his Petition after the War was ended, <hi>Well</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I did not ſerve you ſo at the Battel of</hi> Acteum.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Never imagine to be owned and acknowledged by him, in that great Day, if thou diſſert his Cauſe and Intereſt now, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.33. <hi>He that is aſhamed of Me before men, of him will I be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,</hi> when I come in my Fathers Glory, and mine own Glory, and the Glory of the holy Angels. Oh Sirs, one of theſe dayes the Lord will break out of Heaven with a<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16.</note> ſhout, accompanied with<note n="†" place="margin">Jude <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> myriads of Angels, and ten thouſands of his Saints, thoſe gliſtering Courtiers of Heaven,<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10.</note> the Heavens and Earth in a dreadful conflagration round about him;<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.28.</note> the Graves ſhall open, the Sea and the Earth give up their dead:<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31.</note> Thou ſhalt ſee him aſcend the awful ſeat of Judgement,<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2.</note> his faithful Ones ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the Bench as Aſſeſſors with him:<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.32.</note> All fleſh gathered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him,<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Joel</hi> 3.14.</note> even multitudes, multitudes in that Valley of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion; and then to be publickly diſowned by him in the face of that great Aſſembly, and proclaimed a Traytor and Delinquent to him, that fearedſt not to deny Him, and betray his Truths in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his enemies hands, becauſe of the Frowns of a poor Worm that ſhall die, and be made as graſs; Oh what Confuſion and everlaſting Shame ſhall cover thee! This, this is the portion of all ſuch from the hand of the Lord; 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. <hi>If we deny him, he alſo will deny us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Conſider ere thou let go thy Profeſſion, how remarkably the righteous Hand of Heaven hath met with and payed home the Apoſtate, even in this life; which nevertheleſs, is but as a few drops upon them before the cloud diſſolve, and the whole ſtorm falls, but as the perboiling of them, before they be roaſted in the eternal Flames. See what is become of <hi>Judas, Mat.</hi> 27.3, 4, 5. compared with, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.18. poor <hi>Spira,</hi> though I determine not of his final ſtate, yet what a living monument of wrath was he, whiles he lived; <hi>I feel</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>the very Torments of hell in my ſoul. Lucian</hi> and <hi>Julian,</hi> two ſcoffing Apoſtates, the one torn to pieces by dogs; the other, when mortally wounded by a darr,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:136315:5"/>flings up his blood towards heaven in a way of revenge, and crys, <hi>Thou haſt overcome, O</hi> Galilean.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Suppoſe thou eſcape ſuch a ſtroak, yet never expect a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table hour in this world any more, unleſs the Lord give thee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned repentance to life, which in ſuch caſes is but ſeldom: thou mayeſt have as much comfort in thy enjoyments here, for which thou haſt ſold Chriſt, as <hi>Judas</hi> had in his thirty pieces, or <hi>Spira</hi> in his wife and children; <hi>Mark</hi> 8 35. <hi>Whoſoever will ſave his life, ſhall loſe it (i.e.)</hi> at leaſt, its comfort.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="counsel">
               <head>COUNSEL <hi>II.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Touch not with Idolatry and Superſtition; under what name or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſoever it be preſented to you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1 Joh. 5.21. <hi>Little Children, keep your ſelves from Idols.</hi> Here you had need be exceeding cautelous, and<note n="*" place="margin">qui eavet ne decipatur, vir cavet, cum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam cavet, et cum caviſſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt, ſepe is cautor captus eſt.</note> circumſpect. (1.) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a creeping thing, which works in it ſelf by plauſable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and inſinuations, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23. In which reſpect <hi>[Mystery]</hi> is written in the Whores forehead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5. For as Dr. <hi>Uſher</hi> well obſerves, <hi>The Roman Apoſtacy ſtole into the Church diſguiſed, and by degrees.</hi> It is a Myſtery of Iniquity (ſaith the Apoſtle) and a working Myſtery, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Iniquitas ſed myſtica, pietatis, et fidelitatis nomine palliata; (i. e.)</hi> Iniquity, but a myſtical iniquity, becauſe palliated, and cloaked under the name and pretence of piety and fidelity.<note place="margin">Davenant in Loc.</note> Idolatrous practices have a ſhew of wiſdom, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23. (<hi>i.e.</hi> ſaith <hi>Davenant</hi> on the the place) <hi>They are more modeſt then to pretend an immediate reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Spirit:</hi> yet leſt their placets and inventions, ſhould want a pretext of divine wiſdom, they are wont to ſay, that their Doctrines and Traditions are not indeed conſigned to writing by the Apoſtles, but delivered by lively voice, according to that, <hi>We ſpeak Wiſdom among them that are perfect:</hi> and by the name of this wiſdom, every one calls his own fictions. Saith <hi>Ireneus, Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Thus ſometimes under the pretext of Wiſdom, Order, Decency, Apoſtolical Traditions, Antiquity, the power of the Church,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>it ſteals upon men</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Peditentem, uſu ipſo, et ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cita doctorum approbatione expit eſſe in praecio, hac eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mationae, ſenſim ſine ſenſu creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente.</note> 
                  <hi>inſenſibly, eſpecially being ſo advantaged by the pronity of corrupt nature to it.</hi> To this purpoſe it is obſervable, that Babylon, the Mother of Harlots, is ſaid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.4. to give the Wine of her Fornication in a golden Cup. Wine in it ſelf is temptingly pleaſant, but more, when preſented in a golden Cup; the<note n="*" place="margin">Velati pueris abſynthia te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra medentes, cum dare co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantur prius oras pocula cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum: contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt dulci mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis. flav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quote.</note> brims whereof are ſugared and ſweetned, to make it the more
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:136315:6"/>grateful, Therefore little Children, I mean you ſimple, plain, credulous ſouls, apt to be taken with fine gliſtering things, look to your ſelves; (2.) becauſe nothing more provokes and inflames the fierce Wrath of the Lord, who is a jealous God, than this doth; it makes his anger to come up in his face, as that expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38.18. and kindles conſuming wrath, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.7, 8, 9. Upon this account the bleſſed God complains, after the manner of men, as if his heart were broken, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 6.9. <hi>I am [broken] with their whoriſh heart, and with their [eyes] which go a whoring after their Idols.</hi> If it be but an unchaſte glance upon an Idol, it goes to the very heart of God: when he ſeeth his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple yielding to the temptations of it, he ſhreeks as it were, and crys out, <hi>Oh do not this abominable thing that I hate;</hi> Oh if there be in you the hearts of Children, do not do that, which doth as it were break the heart of your Father.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But what mean you by Idolatry and Superſtition? we hope there are no ſuch things practiſed among us; Pagans and Papiſts may be guilty of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> Give me leave here to open theſe things unto you, and then perhaps you may ſee them nearer to you, then you are aware of; and that this Caution is a word in Seaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idolatry</hi> then,<note place="margin">What Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is.</note> according to the true and generally received de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of it, is,<note n="*" place="margin">Cultus Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligioſus qui exhibitur rei, quae non eſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus deus: vel etiam ipſi-vero Deo, ſed aliter quam ipſe prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripſit in Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo ſuo. <hi>Ravanelus.</hi>
                  </note> A religious Worſhip, given either to that which is not the true god, or to the true God himſelf, but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then he hath preſcribed in his Word. From hence we plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee that worſhip may be idolatrous two wayes; (1.) In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Object, if it have any thing beſides the true God for its object, its groſs Idolatry; ſuch as the firſt Commandment condems. Pagan Idolatry, which the light of the Goſpel hath long ſince profligated, and expelled out of theſe parts of the the world. Or (2.) in reſpect of the Manner, when we worſhip the true God, but in a way and manner which he hath not preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in his Word, but is invented and deviſed by our ſelves; and this is condemned as Idolatry in the<note n="†" place="margin">Eſt autem i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolo latria, cum vel fingitur eſſe Deus et colitar pro Deo quod non eſt, vel cum verus Deus co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litur aliter quam vult coli. <hi>Pareus. Com. in</hi> Rom. <hi>1.23.</hi>
                  </note> ſecond Commandment; <hi>Thou ſhalt not [make to thy ſelf;] (i.e.)</hi> out of thine own brain, or of thine own head, any <hi>[graven Image]</hi> under which title all humane inventions, corrupting the pure and ſimple Worſhip of God, are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:136315:6"/>prohibited, as <hi>idolatrous;</hi> for<note n="*" place="margin">In this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which hath ſo diſquieted the Church in all ages. <hi>ſc.</hi> Who ſhall preſcribe the Form of God's Worſhip ſhall Angels? ſhall Men? ſhall the Church? ſhall Councils? The anſwer is, that when we have choſen Jehovah for our God, and reiected all falſe gods, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his firſt Law, leſt our minds ſhould invent him any ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, he hath here preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Laws him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. for his own moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Service. <hi>Hollands</hi> four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold State of Man, pag. <hi>(mihi)</hi> 31.</note> Images are hereby a Synecdoche put for all falſe wayes of worſhipping God, as the beſt Expoſitors tell us. See <hi>Ameſ. Medulla,</hi> lib. 2. p. 334. <hi>Holland</hi> on the ſecond Com. <hi>Willet, Hexapla</hi> in loc. This inventing or making to our ſelves, is that which makes it Idolatry, <hi>Amos</hi> 5.26. <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.39. Hence the Molten Calf became an Idol to the Iſraelites, not becauſe it was the object of their worſhip; for it's evident, it was <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the true God, they intended to worſhip by it; as appears from <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.4, 5. <hi>To morrow is a feaſt to the Lord.</hi> And as Dr. <hi>Willet</hi> obſerves, it had been impoſſible, that ſo good a man as <hi>Aaron,</hi> would have yielded to them, if they had intended to worſhip it as a god: but yet it being a way or manner of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the true God, which was of their own deviſing, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Idolatry. And this worſhip of God in wayes of our own invention, becomes idolatrous upon a double ground: (1.) As it is Will-worſhip; <hi>(i.e.)</hi> ſuch worſhip as hath no other ground, or warrant, but the will of man,<note n="†" place="margin">Deum amare quidem culto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, hoc eſt, eum qui laetus et lubens ea facit que ipſe fieri juſſit, ſed odiſſe cultum voluntarium, hoc eſt, illa opera que pro immediato Dei cultu illi offeruntur com ab ipſo non fuerent preſcripta et mandata ad hanc finem, hoc enim eſt fornicari in ad inventionibus ſuis. <hi>Pſal. 106.39. Daven. in loc.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23. and ſo dethrones God, by ſetting up the will of the Creature above his, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing the peculiar Honour, and incommunicable Soveraignty, and Glory of the bleſſed God, upon the Creature: For the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Soveraignty of God, which is his Glory, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.15. is manifeſted in two things eſpecially; In his Decrees, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.20. and in his Laws, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.22. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.12. The Lord is our King, and Lawgiver: and there is one Lawgiver. Now by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing any thing by our own Authority, in the Worſhip of God, the Commands of God are made void, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.6. his Royal Law is ſlighted, the Throne of God invaded by the Creature; who will be a Lawgiver too, which can no more be born, then the Heavens can bear two Suns; and God is hereby forgotten; as <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.14. <hi>Iſrael hath forgotten his Maker, and buildeth Temples; (i.e.)</hi> by building <hi>[Temples]</hi> when God had appointed but one Temple. This is as <hi>Melancton</hi> obſerves, <hi>Cum Deo certare, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud inſtituendo;</hi> To ſtrive with God, by inſtituting ſome thing of our own. And <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> notes, <hi>Hom.</hi> 2. in <hi>Rom.</hi> That <hi>it is a greater Sin, in God's Worſhip, to do what we ſhould not, than to omit what we ſhould: For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>by the one we ſhew the difficulty of the Law; but by the other, we charge the Law and Law-giver with fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:136315:7"/>make our ſelves wiſer than God: In the one we ſhew our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in not doing the Will of God; but in the other, our impudence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controul the Wiſdom of God.</hi> And it is, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> phraſes it, lib. 3. cap. 13. <hi>Summam arrogantiam, ſibi vendicare quod humana conditio non recipit;</hi> The higheſt Arrogance, to challenge that to our ſelves, which the condition of a Creature is not capable of. And upon this account it is, that the Indignation and Wrath of God ſmoaks ſo dreadfully againſt ſuch Uſurpers, as in the ſad ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> you ſee, becauſe God is a jealous God: and Jealouſie is the rage of a man. <hi>Zelotes eſt, nolens habere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſortium in amando,</hi> can indure no corrival. This God looks upon as the greateſt, and moſt daring Wickedneſs, that a creature can lightly commit. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9.15. All their Wickedneſs is in <hi>Gilgal. [a pro ſummo] (i.e.)</hi> the height of their wickedneſs is there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there they worſhip'd him according to their <hi>own</hi> devices; which was ſuch an affront to the Wiſdom and Soveraignty of God, that he could by no means bear it. This is called, a ſetting our Threſhold beſides the Lord's Threſhold, <hi>Ezck</hi> 43.8. and the nearer this comes to him, the more it provokes him: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſaid in the ſame Text, <hi>There was a Wall betwixt me and them; (i.e.)</hi> either, it cauſed a Wall of ſeparation betwixt me and them; as it's generally expounded; or elſe it notes, how God is provoked, by bringing their own inventions ſo near him: For in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> it is, <hi>There was but a Wall betwixt me and them.</hi> And hence it is evident, that doctrinal, ſymbolical Ceremonies, I mean ſuch Rites and Ceremonies, as are brought into the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, with a ſpiritual ſignification, meerly upon the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Man; are idolatrous Mixtures and Additions, and ſuch, by which the Lord is dreadfully provoked. It's true, men pretend order and decency, and the power of the Church in ſuch caſes: but as learned <hi>Ameſius</hi> well notes;<note n="*" place="margin">Illa igitur quae pertiuent ad ordinem et decorem, non ita relinquun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur hominum arbitrio, ut poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſint quod ipſislibet, ſub illo no nine Eecleſiis optrudere. <hi>Medulla, p. 345.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Thoſe things which pertain to order and decency, are not ſo left to the Will of man, that they may under. that name, obtrude what they pleaſe upon the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> All the liberty that Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.40. gives us, is but this, To obſerve and perform thoſe things which God hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, in an orderly and comely manner; and not to innovate new things, what, and as many as we pleaſe. And then (2.) it becomes Idolatrous upon this ground alſo, becauſe this daring Impudence of men, in worſhipping God in their own way, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues groſs and carnal notions and conceptions of God. When we deviſe a carnal pompous way of worſhip for him, it's an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:136315:7"/>we have ſet up an Idol-god firſt in our imaginations, one like our ſelves, and utterly unlike the true God; who is a moſt ſimple, pure, ſpiritual Being; and as ſuch, will be worſhipped, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.24. But by deviſing ſuch a fleſhly way of worſhip, I ſay, it is manifeſt, we have fanſied to our ſelves another god, altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther different from that God, revealed to us in the Word. Hence it was that <hi>Joſhuah</hi> told the people, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.19. <hi>Ye cannot ſerve the Lord, ſor he is a jealous God, and will not forgive your ſins; q.d.</hi> you cannot ſerve the true God, till you have gotten right ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of him: You fancy to your ſelves a god made up all of Mercy, as if he had no Juſtice nor Righteouſneſs, to call you to an account for your ſins; and ſo do but worſhip an Idol, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in your own imagination, inſtead of the true God. And if the thing be duely weighed, it will appear as well Idolatry to ſubmit to, and acknowledge the<note n="*" place="margin">Hinc impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite et per in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretationem Dei ipſius, il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum nobis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um conſtitutimus et honorem Deo deb tum deferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus illi, cujus authoritati vel inſtitutis noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inetipſos ſubji<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioſo cultu. <hi>Ameſ. Medul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la. lib. 2. p. 335.</hi>
                  </note> Soveraign Authority of a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in appointing Laws for worſhip; or falling down before an imaginary God, or Idol, formed in our own phantaſie; as to bow to, and worſhip a graven Image, or the ſtock of a tree.</p>
               <p>Now hence you may come to ſee at once, both the nature of this ſecond ſort of Idolatry, and alſo the riſe and original of it; which is nothing elſe but the proud &amp; carnal heart of man, which not willing to contain it ſelf within the limits of the Word, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a plain, ſimple, and ſpiritual way of Worſhip is ruled out; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents to it ſelf, new Rites, Ceremonies, and wayes of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping God, more ſutable and pleaſing to the fleſh. And hence it is, that Idolatry is in Scripture, reckoned a work of the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20. becauſe man naturally having a proud heart, and a working imagination, which depending upon ſenſe, and not elevated and rectified by faith, firſt forms to its ſelf carnal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions and notions of God; and then deviſeth a way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſuitable to thoſe notions of him. So that as one well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves;<note n="†" place="margin">Erroris hoc eſt Principium quod quae nobis. placent, Deoetiam placere putamus; &amp; quae nobis diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicent Deo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam diſplicere Putamus.</note> 
                  <hi>This is the Fountain and Principle of all Error, that men think that thoſe things which pleaſe them, muſt needs pleaſe God; and what diſpleaſeth them, muſt alſo diſpleaſe him.</hi> So that this brat, <hi>Idolatry,</hi> is begotten betwixt a proud carnal heart, and the Devil; who ſince he cannot draw men to the former ſort of Idolatry, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours all he can to entangle; and defile them with this, and that partly out of malice to God, knowing what a dear thing his Worſhip is to him; and partly out of a deſign of ruinng ſuch as he can intice to it: for he knowes their ſorrows ſhall be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.4. and God ſeldom lets it eſcape without ſome remarkable ſtroak.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:136315:8"/>
               <p>Upon the whole then, you plainly ſee, Worſhip may be right as to its Object, and yet Idolatrous in reſpect of the Manner; becauſe the aſſuming of a deſpotical power in this caſe, is not only a ſlighting of that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that royal Law, but as high a piece of Treaſon againſt Jeſus Chriſt, as can lightly be committed by a Creature. I will ſhut up this with two worthy and full Teſtimonies to the truth of the point in hand. The firſt is <hi>Melancton</hi> in loc. <hi>Com. de Ceromon. Humaius,</hi> his words are theſe, and they are grave and weighty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Accedit &amp; hoc,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. Melan. in loc. com. p. 631, 632.</note> 
                  <hi>quod Epiſcopi arrogant ſibi poteſtatem coudendi tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiones, quam tamen non concedit eijs evangeliam,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>non eſt leve crimen tentere Deum, eſt enim non infirmitate labi, ſed contemptu Dei, propoſito ipſius verbo, quaſe cum eo certare, aliud inſtituendo, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, et illius ſapientiae, noſtram anteferre.</hi> The Biſhops arrogate to themſelves a power of making Traditions, whcih the Goſpel hath not given them. It is no ſmall crime to tempt God, for this is not to ſlide by infirmity, but by contempt of God, his Word being ſet before them as it were to contend with it, by inſtituting another thing, and overcome it. This is to prefer our wiſdom to his.</p>
               <p>And a little after (having given ſome inſtances of it) he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds thus;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tales fuerunt et ſunt fontes cultus idolorum. Haec ſunt arccana mala, quae political ſapientia non poteſt judicare, ſed nos in Eccleſia, ea conſiderare debemus; ut moniti, ſubjiciamus nos verbo Dei, nec noſtris opinionibus regi velimus.</hi> Such have been, and are the fountain of the worſhip of Idols. Theſe are ſecret Evils, which political wiſdom cannot judge: but we in the Church, ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe things, that being warned, we may ſubmit our ſelves to the Word of God, and not be willing to be ruled by our own opinions, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To this I ſhall add the moſt worthy Teſtimony of that right Honourable Lord <hi>Brook.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lord Brooks Treatiſe of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy, p. 60, 61.</note>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>A Biſhops wearing a Surplice, Cope, Miter, uſing thè Croſs, bowing to the Altar, &amp;c. (though they may be Errors) yet all, or one of theſe make him not a Pope, or Popling, or properly Antichriſtian; but receiving theſe from the Popes Dictates, doing them becauſe he commands, acknowledging his power in commanding them, preſſing them on others in ſuch a deſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical power, makes a true Pope, a real Antichriſt: Nor may our Biſhops evade by this, which I eaſily ſee will be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:136315:8"/>that though indeed they do, and command theſe things; yet they neither do them from the Popes command, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them in the Popes power.</p>
                  <p>Though I ſhould grant this, which yet many wiſe men will not grant (for our Biſhops firſt power come from the Pope; and of late laſo, we have ſound Letters, Advice, Commands, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates from the Pope, to ſome of our Biſhops, and that in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of greateſt conſequence, both for Church and State:) But grant all this they ſay, yet they may be Antichriſtian, and ſo ſuch <hi>(in re)</hi> as the Pope is; though not literally <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they do or command in the power of <hi>Rome.</hi> This I ſhall be bold to aſſirm, and maintain, till I ſee better reaſon, that he, (who ever he be) that commands the leaſt tittle of Doctrine, or Diſcipline, meerly <hi>ex imperio voluntat is,</hi> in his own power and authority, without licenſe or warrant from Scripture, or right Reaſon (where the Scripture hath been ſilent) though the thing he ſo commandeth, ſhould happen to be good in it ſelf, yet he in his ſo commanding, is not only Tyrannical, but Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, properly Antichriſtian, encroaching on the Royal Office of Chriſt; which is truly High Treaſon againſt God, and moſt properly Antichriſtianiſm.</p>
               </q>
               <p>By all which, you ſee where the Idolatry of Worſhip lies: the inſtituting of any, though the ſmalleſt part of worſhip, in and by our own authority, without Scripture warrant, makes it Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous, as well as if we worſhipped an Idol. And hence it is, that God gives his People the ſame call from this latter ſort of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Idolatry; See <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. as he doth from the more groſs Pagan Idolatry, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. So that if that worſhip you perform to God, be corrupted by a mixture of meer humane, doctrinal, ſymbol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Rites, and Ceremonies which God hath not appointed in his Worſhip, by the Word; though your worſhip be right for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, yet it is Idolatrous in the Manner. Here you had need to be adviſed, and careful, for you are upon a tickliſh point.</p>
               <p>And for ſuperſtition, that is nothing elſe,<note place="margin">What Supes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition is,</note> but an <hi>exceſs in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> For the better underſtanding whereof, conſider three things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That all and every part of God's inſtituted Worſhip, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends intirely upon his own Soveraign Will and Pleaſure: So that no man can appoint any part of it, but God alone, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as no man knowes either what will be acceptable to God, but God himſelf; that which is highly eſteemed among men, is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:136315:9"/>an abomination to God: beſides, none can give efficacy to a Creature, as Bread, Wine, Water, or raiſe them up to ſuch high ſupernatural ends and uſes, but God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Will of God, which is the Foundation and Rule of his Worſhip, is only revealed to us in the Scriptures, whence it is manifeſt, that in Worſhip, all men are bound to keep cloſe to the Word, and beſides the reaſon that is in the thing it ſelf, the Command is expreſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.13. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] according to this Canon, or Rule: This is true Canonical Obedience. So <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.7. [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] is properly Word-Service; <hi>(i.e.)</hi> ſuch as the Word pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence then you may ſee the door at which Superſtition en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, even addition of new and uncommanded things. When we invent new Rites and Ceremonies, and bring them into the Worſhip of God, with a ſpiritual ſignification and uſe, this is Superſtition; being <hi>[Supra Statutum]</hi> ſomething above and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what God appoints and requires. And as all the water in <hi>Tyber,</hi> cannot waſh the Papiſts from the Filth of their Idolatry and Superſtition, in their <hi>Maſs, Altars, Surplice, Croſs, &amp;c.</hi> So neither can any thing beſides the Blood of Jeſus, cleanſe us from the ſame, if we do like them.</p>
               <p>Having thus opened the nature of Idolatry and Superſtition to you, I ſhall reinforce that Apoſtolical Caution upon you; <hi>Little Children, keep your ſelves from Idols;</hi> I beſeech you get ſenſes exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14. and ſuffer not your ſelves to be abuſed by an eaſie credulity: <hi>The ſimple believeth every word,</hi> Prov. 14.15. There is no Idolatry or ſuperſtition in <hi>Rome</hi> ſo groſs, but is gloſt over with plauſable pretences, and many ſubtile<note n="*" place="margin">Additio cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumpens, et conſervans. Additio acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentalium, et eſſentialium.</note> diſtinctions inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to defend it. But take not you any thing upon truſt in God's Worſhip; be like thoſe well-bred <hi>Bereans, Acts</hi> 17.11. examine the grounds-of your practice. It was a good ſaying of Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Moor, I will pin my Faith</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>upon no mans ſleeve, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I know not whether he will carry it.</hi> See that you be provided with an anſwer, if God ſhould ſpeak to you, when you are at your <hi>Divine Service,</hi> as he did to <hi>Elijah,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.9. when he was hid in the Cave at <hi>Horeb, What doſt thou here, Elijah?</hi> Or as to the <hi>Jews, Iſa.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Who hath required this at your hands?</hi> See that you be able by the Word, to juſtifie your practice: and as you love your ſouls, defile them not with Idolatiy, or Superſtition. And the rather;</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:136315:9"/>
               <p>Becauſe, ſhould you be found in a falſe way of worſhip,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 1.</note> you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray a ſpecial truſt committed to you by the Lord.</p>
               <p>Chriſtians, unto you hath the Lord committed his precious Goſpel-Truths and Appointments, as precious Treaſure, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and keep for him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Jude</hi> 3. 1 <hi>Phil.</hi> 7.17. and one ſpecial means of its preſervation, is by witneſſing againſt all thoſe Errours and Innovations, that corrupt and endanger it: O ſee that none of Chriſt's Jewels be embezled, if you can help it. You your ſelves have committed a truſt to Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. and expect he ſhould be faithful in what you have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to him; and he expects the ſame from you. Oh! conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what precious things the pure Inſtitutions of Chriſt are:<note place="margin">Ruat Caelum, potius quam una mica veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis percat. <hi>Luth.</hi>
                  </note> all the good in this world, cannot compenſate the loſs of one of them. <hi>Let Heaven ruſh</hi> (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) <hi>rather than one crumb of Truth ſhould periſh.</hi> Oh what hard things have the Saints in all generations ſuffered, to preſerve and tranſmit it to us! and ſhall we now betray it? would not the generations to come curſe us, and abhor our remembrance? And then to ſpeak nothing of any ſolemn bond or engagement under which you have put your ſouls to the contrary.</p>
               <p>Shall we not hereby oppoſe and croſs the great Deſign which God is carrying on in the world, by his preſent Providences?<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 2.</note> Oh 'twill be ſad to be found oppoſing God's Deſign! Now what is that but, by<note n="*" place="margin">Tali concuſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ad primam Chriſti adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum viam pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravit, tali e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ad ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. Magnus antehac fecit rerum mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, ſed reſtat, longe major. <hi>Grotius.</hi>
                  </note> ſhaking Heaven and Earth, to remove the things that are <hi>[made;] viz.</hi> by man invented in his Worſhip, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.27. To pluck up by the roots, every <hi>[Plant;] (i.e.)</hi> Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Tradition not of his planting, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.13. Are not all theſe things appointed to perdition? <hi>Col.</hi> 2.22. and dareſt thou then by thy preſence, or pleading for them, go about to ſupport and eſtabliſhe them, and ſo ſtrive againſt God? Oh conſider it ſadly.</p>
               <p>Is it not dangerous to be found amongſt Idolaters?<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 3.</note> doth not Judgment ſometimes ſweep away the whole community and neighbourhood of ſuch ſinners? Read 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.19, 20. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.13. And hath not God given thee timely warning of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger before it come? <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. and is it not more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dangerous, to be found among them now, when God is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring his Troops to invade <hi>Babylon;</hi> I mean ready to pour forth the Vials of his Wrath upon Her?</p>
               <p>And may not your example have a miſchievous influence upon others? may it not harden ſinners in their wayes?<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 4.</note> and even
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:136315:10"/>compel and draw away the weak Chriſtian? <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.13, 14. and ſo draw the guilt of their ſins upon thine own ſoul? and what a dreadful thing is that!<note n="†" place="margin">Acceſſorium ſequitor natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Principo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Agentes &amp; Conſentientes, paripaena plec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuntur.</note> Actors and Conſenters are alike guilty and puniſhable: Oh you have too much perſonal guilt of your own, add not the guilt of others ſins to it: nay, by this means, thou mayeſt be ſinning in another, when thou lyeſt in the duſt.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, conſider how careful God hath alwayes been to keep his People off, at the greateſt diſtance from Idolatry. Compare theſe Scriptures, 2 <hi>King</hi> 17.15. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.20. <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.38. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.1. O let theſe Arguments be impartially weighed, and let not any low fleſhly intereſt, be ſet up to oppoſe them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="counsel">
               <head>COUNSEL <hi>III.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beware of ſuch perſons as are Factors and Agents for Antichriſt, and keep off from ſuch a Miniſtry, the tendency and ſcope of which, is to entice and draw you to Idolatry,</hi> Mat. 7.15. &amp; 10.17. Phil. 3.2. Col. 2.8.</p>
               <p>There is a<note n="*" place="margin">It is not my deſign to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe any god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſon, that by the preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation may joyn w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> them; the Lord I hope will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover ſuch out of the ſnare but I ſpeak. of the body, and generality of them.</note> generation of men now abroad, skilful to deſtroy ſouls, who would make Merchandiſe of you, and by good words and fair ſpeeches, deceive the hearts of the ſimple [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,] ſuch as mean well, but want prudence to diſcern ſuch as mean ill. Theſe are of two ſorts; the generality of them are by a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hand of God, given over to ſuch diſſoluteneſs and debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that their folly and madneſs, is made manifeſt to all men, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9. And others that have gifts and parts, how few are there of them, but imploy them in defending abominable Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions, and perſwading their Congregations to ſubmit to them: So that you have your choice, whether you will drink poyſon mixt with water, or infuſed into brisk and generous wine, which will give it a ſpeedier acceſs to the ſpirits. Theſe are<note n="†" place="margin">Jactant cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, ſed eam non intelligunt, imo pervertunt apperiunt quaſi fontes ſcientiae, qui aquam non habent doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum, praemit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt imbrem, velut nubes prophetiae. <hi>Hieion. contra Jov.</hi>
                  </note> Wells without water, deceiving the hope of weary and thirſty ſouls: Clouds they are without rain, that ſend not forth one gracious ſhower to refreſh the Inheritance of the Lord: The beſt of them is a bryar, and the moſt upright of them ſharper than a thorne hedge, <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.4.</p>
               <p>I believe there be many among you that are ſharp ſet, and by this time have felt the miſery of a ſpiritual famine. 'Tis bread you come for, but your Father hath ſhut up houſe, and is gone for a time, the Glory is departed; they are become Wells without water, breaſts without milk: is there not a vanity in theſe, as well as in the creatures, when God is withdrawn from them?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:136315:10"/>We may ſay concerning them, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> did to his father, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.7. <hi>Behold the fire and the wood, but where is the Sacrifice?</hi> Here you may ſee the skin, and ſhadow of an Ordinance, but where is the power? where is the life, quickening, and ſoul refreſhment, that was wont to accompany them? Ah poor <hi>England!</hi> what haſt thou loſt! what a Miniſtry haſt thou ſinned away! waſt thou not renowned among the Nations for the power, and purity of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances? were not thy Miniſters as ſheep coming up from the waſhing, whereof every one bare twins, and none was barren among them? How was the Lord Jeſus lifted up in thy Miniſtry, that all might ſee the Neceſſity, Beauty and Excellency of him! and did not the pangs of the <hi>New-birth,</hi> frequently come upon ſouls in thine Aſſemblies? But alas, thoſe dayes are over, they are gone, they are gone; ah wo is us, that we muſt ſay, <hi>So it was!</hi> Well then, what will you do in this caſe? will you ſeek the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving among the dead? will you ſuck empty breaſts, whence you can draw nothing but wind or blood? O no, but rather ſay, as <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Tell me, O thou whom my ſoul loveth, where thou feedeſt, where thou makeſt thy Flocks to reſt at noon; for why ſhould I be as one that turns aſide by the flocks of thy companions?</hi> Theſe Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſt, muſt be none of yours.</p>
               <p>Becauſe it is the manifeſt drift, and deſign of their Miniſtry,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 1.</note> to unteach, and beguile you of thoſe precious Goſpel-Truths which you have formerly received, and learnt. This ſome of them have not ſhun'd to declare in the face of their Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and nothing is more apparent, than that it is the deſign they all manage. I appeal to your own obſervations, what is more common with them, than to tell you, you have been miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided by your Teachers theſe twenty years, and now muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the good Old Way, which themſelves are utterly unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with?</p>
               <p>Now what do you by attendance on ſuch a Miniſtry, but run your ſouls upon a temptation to unſettlement, and Apoſtacy? and dig a grave (as I may ſay) to bury all the precious Truths you have learn'd under your former faithful Miniſters? Who may ſigh over you, and ſay, as <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> did, when he was in <hi>Oxford,</hi> at the coming in of Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> he heard a Colledge-Bell ring to Maſs, and looking out at his Study window, ſaw the Scholars flocking apace to it, being ſtruck to the heart with this ſight, he brake out into this expreſſion,<note place="margin">Pet. Martyr.</note> 
                  <hi>Haec una notula</hi> (ſaid he) omnem meam doctrinam evertit; (i.e.) This Bell rings a paſſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:136315:11"/>to all my Doctrine: and upon ſerious conſideration, this will appear to be no ſmall evil. For you cannot but be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that it is your duty to be immoveably fixed in the Truths of the Goſpel which you have received, and to ſuffer no man to ſpoil you of them: if you doubt that, read 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17, 18. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6, 7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58.</p>
               <p>And if this be your ſin, to be moved away from it, then it muſt needs be your duty, to avoid the temptations, means and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of ſuch unſettlement. And this is that which is intended in all thoſe cautions given in the Word, and but lately recited.</p>
               <p>I am againſt the Prophets that <hi>[ſteal]</hi> the Word, every man from his neighbour, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.30, He means the falſe true Prophets that enticed the People from thoſe Truths, which the Prophets had taught them. There be ſpiritual Cut-purſes abroad, pray look to your ſelves: the old <hi>Chemarims</hi> are revived again in this Generation: the word, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.4. is conceived to come from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>incaluit; (i. e.)</hi> men more zealous and hot than ordinary, for their ſuperſtitious Traditions; inflam'd with deſires to draw you to it: <hi>Ut multitudine ſequacium, ſeſe efferunt:</hi> Which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle engliſhes, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.13. that they may glory in your fleſh: And therefore beware of men.</p>
               <p>Doth not your attendance upon,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 2.</note> and following of ſuch a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, help to midwive and bring forth all thoſe evils with which their Miniſtry travels, and is in pain to be delivered of? could they do any hurt, if they were generally declined and avoided? their ſtrength lyeth in you: As a great Commander once ſaid to his Souldiers, <hi>That he flew upon their Wings.</hi> Hence it was the <hi>Phariſees</hi> were ſo often diſappointed in their attempts to lay hands upon Chriſt; they had a ſtrong deſign to do it, but the Text ſaith, <hi>They could not becauſe of the People,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 14.2. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 14.2. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.21. So the falſe Teachers in <hi>Jeroboams</hi> time, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.6, 7. were as hot as an Oven, with deſires and deſigns to draw the People to falſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but the People were a great Lump, and could not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be leavened; and therefore in the mean time, till that were done, the Baker ſlept, and ceaſed from raiſing. This for a time, obſtructed the deſign. But here is the miſery, the people are <hi>materia diſpoſita,</hi> matter fit for them to work into any form, if they give them but an heat or two in a plauſable Sermon, they are mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liable, and fit to be hammered into any ſhape, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. <hi>ult. The People love to have it ſo:</hi> And <hi>Amos</hi> 4.5. This-liketh you, <hi>O houſe of Iſrael.</hi> Fear of Perſecution makes them comply with any thing, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.12.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:136315:11"/>
               <p>Can you attend lawfully and comfortably upon ſuch a Miniſtry,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 3.</note> upon which you cannot pray for, or expect a bleſſing? doubtleſs, you will readily confeſs you may not. And can you pray for, or expect a bleſſing, where you have no promiſe in all the Book of God, to warrant or encourage you ſo to do? 'tis as clear you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. Now produce but one promiſe made to the labours of ſuch as God hath not ſent. A curſe upon their labours you may find, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.32. and upon their gifts and parts. And a prohibition of hearing them, you may find, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.16. But no promiſe of a bleſſing; that only attends a Miniſtry of Chriſts own ſending, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But hath not Chriſt ſent them? how ſhall we be ſatisfied in that?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider what is requiſite and neceſſary in the ſending,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> or due Call of a Miniſter. (1.) Whether it be perſonal Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, deſcribed, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.7. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. <hi>John</hi> 21.15, 16, 17. (2.) Or free Election by the Church, to which the Miniſtry is given. See <hi>Acts</hi> 1.23, 24. <hi>Acts</hi> 6.5. (3.) Or (according to true Presbyterian Principles) Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, by Faſting, Prayer, and Impoſition of Hands, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.6. &amp; 13.3. &amp; 14.23. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. &amp; 4.14. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.</p>
               <p>If the Sending or Call of a Miniſter, conſiſt in all or either of theſe, than judge your ſelves whether theſe men are ſent. For their Gifts and Qualifications neceſſary to fit them for ſuch a work, let their Congregations witneſs, who are fed upon husks, and ſtarved under them.</p>
               <p>For their Election by the Church, let the Godly in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Pariſhes witneſs, whether they were elected by them, or obtruded upon them, and ſo ſtand upon the ruines of their own lawful and godly Paſtours.</p>
               <p>And for their Ordination, their own Canons may inform you: Wherein it is ordered; (1.) That they be made Deacons; (2.) Then after a years ſpace, they muſt be preſented to the Biſhop, or his Suffragan, by an Arch Deacon or his Deputy, ſaying, <hi>Reverend Father in God, I preſent theſe perſons to be admitted to the Order of Prieſthood.</hi> (3.) Then after the Lettany and ſome Collects, the <hi>Prelate</hi> asketh them, <hi>Do you think in your hearts, that you be truly called according to the Will of Chriſt, and the Order of this Church of</hi> England, <hi>to the Miniſtry of Prieſthood?</hi> and every one of them anſwers, <hi>I think it.</hi> (4.) Then they promiſe reverently, to obey their Ordinary and other chief Miniſters of the Church. (5.) And then kneeling down at the Prelates feet, he, with the Prieſts preſent, lay their hands on their heads, ſaying, <hi>Receive the holy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:136315:12"/>Ghoſt. Whoſe ſins thou doſt forgive, they are forgiven; and whoſe ſins thou doſt retain, they are retained: and be thou a faithful Diſpenſer of the Word of God, and of his holy Sacraments, In the Name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghost.</hi> Amen. (6.) Then delivering to each of them a Bible, he ſaith, <hi>Take thou Authority to preach the Word of God, and to adminiſter the holy Sacraments, in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion where thou ſhalt be ſo appointed.</hi> (7.) And after all this, by the Canons of 1603. none of them are to be admitted to any Eccleſiaſtical Living, or ſuffered to preach, except he be licenſed ſo to do, by the Arch-Biſhop, or Biſhop of the Dioceſs, and ſhall ſubſcribe, <hi>That the Book of Common-Prayer, and of ordering Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, contains in it nothing contrary to the Word of God, and that it may be lawfully uſed, and that he himſelf will uſe the ſame; And that he alloweth the Book of Articles of Religion.</hi> (8.) And then laſtly, having abjured the Covenant, &amp;c. he is a compleat Prieſt to all Intents and Purpoſes.</p>
               <p>Judge now what a fair and regular Call here is to the Miniſtry. I remember <hi>Aquinas</hi> tells us, that, <hi>If the Artificers Hand were his Rule, he could never work amiſs.</hi> And ſo, if the Prelates Hand be the Rule of Ordination, they cannot but be well ordained: but if the Scriptures be indeed the Rule, I am at a loſs where to find a Text parallel to this Practice, unleſs it be that in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.9. which, I confeſs, ſuits it to an hairs breadth.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But this will invalidate and nullifie the Call of our former ancient and godly Miniſters, for they came in the ſame way: Yet God hath owned them, and they have made full proof of their Miniſtry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> Not at all. For (1.) though it muſt be confeſt (and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves will not deny, but there were many grand Irregularities in their Ordination; yet it was (comparatively) a time of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and darkneſs; and in ſuch caſes, God is more indulgent, and the ſin receives not ſuch aggravations, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.5, 6, 7. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.17. (2.) As hard as the terms then were, they are harder now by far: ſeveral things ſince that, have inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened, which are conſiderable. (3.) They were holy men, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified with Graces and Gifts, able and apt to teach, which is mainly conſiderable in a Miniſters Call. (4.) Laſtly, they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally came into their places at the deſire, and upon the call, of the moſt godly perſons in the places where they lived. And this, if they had no more, makes them true Miniſters (in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of many judicious Divines) although their Epiſcopal Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination ſhould be a nullity. Let us here what is ſaid in this caſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:136315:12"/>by others. <hi>Ameſius,</hi> his words are theſe, ſpeaking to this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; In whom is this right, and power of calling the Miniſters? he anſwers; (1.) <hi>Summum jus vocationis, eſt penes Chriſtum ſolum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ameſ.</hi> Caſ. conſci. lib. 4. p. 233.</note> 
                  <hi>qui eſt Eccleſiae caput, &amp; Miniſterij auctor, ac Dominus Miniſtrorum.</hi> (2.) <hi>Jus delegatum non poteſt proprie eſſe vel Epiſcoporum Diaeceſano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vel Patranorum, vel Magis tratuum, qua ſunt tales; quia Chriſtus qui Miniſterium inſtituit, de iſtis ordinibus nihil ſingulare preſcripſit, nihil novi juris ipſis communicavit, et Eccleſiam ſine illis optime ordinatam reliquit.</hi> (3.) <hi>Jus delegatum eſt Penes Eccleſiam illam totam, cui Miniſter vocandus debit inſervire,</hi> &amp;c. (1.) The chief right of calling, is the Power of Chriſt alone, who is Head of the Church, Author of the Miniſtry, and Lord of Miniſters. (2.) The delegated right cannot properly be, either of dioceſan Biſhops, or Patrons, or Magiſtrates (as ſuch) becauſe Chriſt, who inſtituted the Miniſtry, preſcribed nothing ſingular, concerning thoſe Orders, communicated nothing of any new right to them, and left his Church well ordered without them. (3.) The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legated Right is in the power of that whole Church, to which the Miniſter that is to be called, ought to ſerve, &amp;c. Which he proves by many weighty Arguments. To this I ſhall joyn the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of that bleſſed man, now with God, Mr. <hi>Jer. Burroughs,</hi> his words are theſe; <q rend="inline">For their calling; I make no queſtion,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Burroughs</hi> on the <hi>11th</hi> of <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>2d</hi> Book, p. 110.</note> but there are many Miniſters in <hi>England,</hi> as they were, and as they are, that are the true Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, and have a true Call from Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>Object. <hi>But how can that be? they hold their ſtanding from the Biſhops, and ſo from Antichriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">Take it for granted, that their Authority from the Biſhops was wholly naught, and ſinful, yet that doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but that many Miniſters, that had their Ordination from them, are true Miniſters of Chriſt: Why? not becauſe of that they had from them, but they had their calling likewiſe from the People of God, as well as in a ſeeming way from them: for we will take that for granted, that that they had from them, there was ſuch corruption in it, that they ſinned againſt God; but yet mark, that doth not nullifie their Call, becauſe they had ſomewhat ſuper-added, wherein they ſinned againſt God.</q> This he farther illuſtrates in the ſame place by this ſimilitude, <hi>If a man have two Deeds or Evidences for a piece of Land, and one be naught,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Collins vindiciae Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt, <hi>p. 73.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>yet if the other be good and ſound, he hath a true Title.</hi> Mr. <hi>Collings</hi> alſo, anſwering this Objection, <hi>Miniſters had their Ordination from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:136315:13"/>Biſhops, and they from Rome. Rome is no true Church, and hath no true Miniſtry; and thoſe that were not Miniſters themſelves, could not make others.</hi> Having inferr'd ſeveral abſurdities from the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, gives this anſwer; <q rend="inline">Suppoſe the Reformers had no Ordination, but the Call of the People, it was a plain caſe of neceſſity; and they had power doubtleſs, to reſtore that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance to the Church again.</q>
               </p>
               <p>So that as long, as they were holy men, ſo eminently qualified, and fairly called by good People, far be it from me, to queſtion the validity of their Call. But the Caſe before us, differs Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-wide from this.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But they are not worſe than the Scribes and Phariſees were? yet Chriſt commands his Diſciples to hear them,</hi> Mat. 23.2, 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> Becauſe this is the <hi>Achilean</hi> Argument, I ſhall endeavour to ſatisfie you in this Scripture, and deſtroy the Argument com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly drawn from this place, by theſe plain and (as I judge) ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory replies to it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thoſe that infer from this Text a duty or a liberty of atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on, or joyning with a prophane and corrupt Miniſtry, do thereby (though perhaps unawares) gratifie the Popiſh Cauſe and Intereſt; for from this very Text, they draw many of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to condemn our ſeparation from them, and alſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us of the neceſſity of obeying the Mandates of their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, and hearing their Jeſuites and Monks, notwithſtanding their corruptions in worſhip, and filthy ſodomitical lives. <hi>Huc enim torquent verba Chriſti,</hi> ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> To this ſenſe they wreſt the words of Chriſt. And to the ſame ſence <hi>Pareus</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Ut hodie Papa, et Epiſcopi clamant, omnia, omnia ſervate;</hi> As the Pope and the Biſhops cry out at this day, all things, all things they bid you do, obſerve and doe. So that by taking the words in ſuch a large unlimitted ſenſe, we do the Cauſe of Chriſt more diſſervice, than we are aware of.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is further conſiderable, that the Arguments drawn from this Text, are commonly fallacious, taking it for granted, that religious hearing, as an act of worſhip, is here injoyned; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is not a ſyllable of any ſuch thing in the Text: Indeed Chriſt bids them obſerve and do whatſoever they bid them; but it doth not thence follow, they ſhould religiouſly attend on their Miniſtry: (1.) Becauſe its evident, theſe Scribes and Phariſees ſuſtained a double capacity; they were Expoſitors of the Law, that we allow; and they were alſo of the Sanedrim, in a civil
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:136315:13"/>capacity, as Rulers; that appears from, <hi>John</hi> 3.1.10. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.34. In this civil capacity, they are moſt properly ſaid, to ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Seat: for the 70 Elders which made up this Sanedrim came in upon a civil ſcore at firſt, as appears from, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.16, 17. and ſo were joyned with <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Government. Now then, this command ſeems moſt properly to reſpect them as Rulers; who in that capacity both opened the judicial Laws of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and enjoyned the people to obey them. (2.) Becauſe Chriſt had before warned them, to take heed of their leaven <hi>(i.e.)</hi> their Doctrine, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.6, 12. and told them they were blind Guides, and what the fatal iſſue of them and their Diſciples that followed them, would be, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.14. both ſhould fall into the ditch; and that their worſhip was vain, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9. and it is not like he would afterwards encourage them to attend on it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But admit it were ſo, that Chriſt gives them liberty to hear them as Miniſters, though they were corrupt, yet it is no good conſequence, that therefore we may hear any Miniſters, though never ſo corrupt in principles and practice now. And the reaſon which deſtroyes this conſequence, is this, becauſe there is a vaſt difference betwixt the infant State of the Goſpel-Church in the dayes of Chriſt on earth, and its more perfect State after his death; we know the firſt Tabernacle was then ſtanding, the Vail of the Temple not then rent in twain, the Goſpel-Miniſtry not then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted: and therefore during that State, as Chriſt himſelf ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Ordinances of the Law <hi>(for it became him to fulfill all Righteouſneſs:)</hi> ſo did his Diſciples ſubmit to them alſo: yea, and he exhorts others alſo, to obſerve the rites appointed by it; as <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.4. bids him that was cleanſed, to go and ſhew himſelf to the Prieſt, and offer his Gift which the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> required. But ſince the death of Chriſt, and the taking down of that firſt Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, and the inſtitution of the Goſpel-Miniſtry, none of theſe Precepts bind: for, as Judicious <hi>Pareus</hi> on the place notes, this was but <hi>[Mandatum temporale]</hi> a temporal Command; which ceaſed to oblige upon the commiſſionating and full inſtruction of the New Goſpel-Miniſtry: <hi>And then it's manifeſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they made a Separation from the Phariſees, and the Jewiſh Synagogue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now we are to attend upon no Miniſtry, but of Chriſt's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; for to them only hath he promiſed his Preſence, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>ult.</hi> and none can preach <hi>(i.e.)</hi> lawfully except he be ſent, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. And I have proved before, theſe are not his Miniſtry, nor ſent by him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="counsel">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:136315:14"/>
               <head>COUNSEL IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Give your uttermoſt diligence to promote Religion, and the Power of Godlineſs, in your reſpective Families, and Neighbourhoods; and the rather do this with all your might, becauſe the ordinary and more publick means of their Converſion and Edification, is cut off.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Counſel conſiſts of two Branches; the firſt concerns your Families, the ſecond your Neighbours: a word diſtinctly to each.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to your Families, O ſhine as Lights there; lay out your Talents as many wayes as they may poſſibly be improveable for the good of all about you, eſpecially thoſe under your guardian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and charge, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.10. By this the Power of Godlineſs muſt be diſcovered in you, and begotten and kept alive in them. The Jews have a Tradition, that the Fire of the Altar was mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly preſerved under ground, during the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity. I am ſure this is the way to preſerve Religion alive, now the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ordinary means are ceaſed. Precepts are not wanting to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force this duty upon you; <hi>Deut</hi> 4.9, 10. &amp; 6.6, 7. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.24, 26, 27. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 4.6, 7, 21, 22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.5, 6. <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4. nor yet worthy Examples to encourage to it; <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19.1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9. <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.26.2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> had a Church in their houſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.19. <hi>Nymphas</hi> and <hi>Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in theirs, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Philem.</hi> 2. <hi>Hence it is,</hi> ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">Adjungit ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialem Saluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, ob ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialem et exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miam hujus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri pietatem, equum enim eſt extra ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um illis deferre honorem, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum egr gia virtus prae cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris eminet et effulget in Eccleſia. <hi>Day. in Loc.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Davenant</hi> on the place, <hi>that the Apoſtle ſends a ſpecial Salutation to them, by name; becauſe of their ſingular Piety, which manifeſted it ſelf in their family Government.</hi> And indeed, how freſh and glorious a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance in the Scriptures have thoſe worthy Saints unto this day, and ſo ſhall have where ever the Goſpel is preached, unto the end of the World; who have burned with an holy Zeal, not only to offer up themſelves, but their families alſo unto God! <hi>David</hi> well underſtood how near this Duty lay to the heart of Religion, when he puts his ſoul under the bond of ſuch a ſolemn engagement to the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.2. It doth not a little affect me to read what a<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Buxtorf.</hi> in Synog. Judaic. Cap. 3.</note> learned man obſerves of the <hi>Jews; Although Religion be miſerably deformed among them, yet it ſeems there are ſome prints of their ancient family Diſcipline to this day remaining among them; for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they are ſo careful to teach their Children in their tender years, the Law, and Books of Moſes, and after that their Talmudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Traditions, as that their skill in Judaiſm at</hi> 17. <hi>exceeds the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of many among us in Chriſtianity, at</hi> 70. Nay, the very <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> boaſt themſelves, the grand Conſervators of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, in that they are Catechiſers. Oh let this Provoke
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:136315:14"/>Cariſtians! we ſee how light breakes out more and more in every age; as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, <hi>I ſee more than bleſſed</hi> Auſtin ſaw; <hi>and they that come after me, will ſee more than I ſee.</hi> And we have great hopes and expectations of the young Generation, that they may enter into the good Land, though we ſhould die in this Wilderneſs. O then let us labour to prepare &amp; make them ready for the Lord; and that not only by inſtructing them in the Principles of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in a Catechiſtical way (though that be an Ordinance of God, and of ſingular uſe in its kind) but by endeavouring to the utmoſt, by Counſels, Perſwaſions, Prayers, for and with them, to have the Power of Godlineſs wrought in their hearts, to travel with them again in pain, till Chriſt he formed in them, And to this Duty, theſe Arguments among many others, may perſwade.</p>
               <p>From the relation it ſelf, which is betwixt you and them;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 1.</note> look but into your own bowels, and you ſhall find arguments enough to provoke your utmoſt care and induſtry for their good: What is a Child but a piece of your ſelf (as one ſaith) wrapt up in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther skin? what an ineſtimable value doth nature it ſelf teach you to ſet upon them.<note place="margin">See Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to Catech. by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Iſle of Weight. p. 17.</note> The life of <hi>Jacob</hi> is ſaid to be bound up in <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mins, Gen.</hi> 44.30. This dear &amp; ardent affection to them, we uſe to expreſs by our earneſt deſires of them, till we have them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.2. <hi>What wilt thou give me, ſeeing I go childleſs,</hi> ſaid <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 30.1. <hi>Give me Children, or elſe I die,</hi> ſaid <hi>Rachel.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.10, 11. How earneſtly did <hi>Hannah</hi> pray in the bitterneſs of her ſoul, for a Child. Alſo by the ſingular contentment we take in them, when we have them, <hi>John</hi> 16.21. and the wonderful tenderneſs of our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to them, and earneſt deſires to keep them, no value can be ſet upon a Child, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.36, 38. <hi>Luke</hi> 8.41, 42. <hi>John</hi> 7.47, 49. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by our ſympathizing with them in all conditions; their comfort is ours, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.27, 28. and their miſery is ours, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.22. And laſtly, by our extream grief when we loſe them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.33, 34, 35. <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.18.</p>
               <p>Now are they ſuch near and dear things to you, Oh then how many motives doth this dear and tender relation wrap up in it, to endeavour the eternal Salvation of their poor Souls! 'tis the Soul of the Child, that is the Child; and if that periſh for want of knowledge, where is the mercy of having Children? ſurely an untimely birth is better than they: Ah when you ſhall ſee them enemies to God, thoſe that came out of your bowels to be in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt him; will it not make you take up <hi>Jobs</hi> wiſh, and apply it to them; let the day periſh wherein they were born,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 3.1, 5.</note> and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:136315:15"/>the night in which it was ſaid they are conceived, let the darkneſs and the ſhadow of death ſtain it; let a cloud dwell upon it, let the blackneſs of the day terrifie it, why dyed they not from the womb? why did they not give up the Ghoſt when they came out of the the belly? why did the knees prevent them? or why the breaſts that they ſhould ſuck? Ah if you have the hearts of Parents in you, think how ſad a conſideration this will be to you, that thoſe who are ſo dear to you, ſhould be the objects of God's Wrath; thoſe you have been ſo tender over, and have ſo often put into your boſomes, muſt underlye eternal torments, and their bed be made in Hell? if you have any good thing your ſelves, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with-hold it from them; if you be feaſted abroad, and they pining at home, the greateſt dainties do you no good. Why now, unleſs they be taught the knowledge of Chriſt, &amp; a ſaving change paſs upon them, when you ſhall ſit down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> in the Kingdom of God, abundantly ſatisfied with the Fatneſs of his Houſe, and drinking of the Rivers of his Pleaſure, they ſhall be ſhut out: Nature teacheth you to feel the pains of their bodies, and cannot Grace teach you to ſympathize with the miſery of their poor wretched Souls? Well, the day is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if they die Chriſtleſs, that they will wiſh they had been the generation of <hi>Tygers,</hi> or off-ſpring of <hi>Dragons,</hi> rather than your Children: and when you can have them no more, you know who muſt, and will.</p>
               <p>From that exceeding Joy,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 2.</note> it muſt needs be to a godly Parent, to ſee his Children, and Relations gracious. May not every god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Parent ſay as <hi>John</hi> did of the Children of the Elect Lady, <hi>I have no greater joy, than to ſee them walk in the Truth,</hi> 2 <hi>John</hi> 1.4. Is it pleaſing to you to ſee your own image in them? and will it not much more delight you, to ſee the Image of Chriſt in them? Grace doubles the relation, and ſo muſt needs exceedingly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe your joy in them. This is the true way to build up the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of your iſſue. How many anxious thoughts and ſollicitous cares, will this diſcharge thy heart of! O if thou leave them in the Covenant of Grace, thy heart may be at reſt concerning them; if thou leave them not a groat, they ſhall not want a father to care for them when thou art in the duſt. Beſides, Grace will ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually teach them the duties of their relation to you, while you live; hereby you will provide, not only for their eternal good, but your own joy alſo.</p>
               <p>The work lyes now upon your hand more than ever,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 3.</note> as I hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:136315:15"/>before; and truly you have many ſingular advantages above all others, to do the work. (1.) You are continually with them, and ſo may take the fitteſt ſeaſons to drop your admonitions upon them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.6, 7. (2.) You beſt know their tempers and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, and ſo can apply your ſelves with more advantage to them. (3.) You have the deepeſt intereſt in their hearts and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which is a great matter, this will make your words, (eſpecially if dropt upon them with much affection) ſink deep. Oh what Child can chuſe but relent, while a Parent it ſpeaking with a melting heart to him, about his Eternal Concernments. I remember <hi>Auſtine</hi> writes of his Mother <hi>Monica,</hi> that ſhe plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Precepts of Life in his mind by her words, watred them with her Tears, and nouriſhed them with her Example. A preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pattern for all Mothers.</p>
               <p>Me thinks theſe Arguments ſhould excite you to your duty; O if you have in you the bowels of Parents, let them impel you to it; you cannot plead danger here, as in other duties; againſt ſuch there is <hi>[yet]</hi> no Law.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to your Neighbourhood. You ſhould ſtudy to be uſeful in your generation; are there any poor carnal Neighbours about you? O viſit them, and be ever dropping ſome ſerious words of Counſel upon them: how do you know but tere may be ſome ſleeping conviction left upon them by the Miniſtry they once ſate under, which you may be inſtrumental to awaken? And are there any that feat the Lord near you, O be often together, ſtrengthen the hands that hand down. The Jews have a Proverb. that <hi>One dry ſtick will ſet two green ones on fire.</hi> A lively Chriſtian may be of ſingular uſe in ſuch a day as this. In <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. we find what the practice of Chriſtians was in an evil day, as it appears that was, by the <hi>15th verſe, They that work wickedneſs, are ſet up, yea they that tempt God, are even delivered.</hi> And yet, <hi>Then they that feared the Lard, ſpake often one to another, and the Lord hearkened and heard it, and a book of remembrance was written before him, for them that feared the Lord, and that thought upon his Name. &amp; And they ſhall be mine,</hi> &amp;c. Oh how well doth God take it, when his People will not be terrified from their Duty by the <hi>fear</hi> of men! <hi>The Lord hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened and heard it; They did not whiſper ſo in one anothers ear</hi> (ſaith a modern Divine) <hi>but God overheard them;</hi> the Lord liſtned, as it were, at the key-hole, he was under the window, and kept it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on record; a book of remembrance was written. Oh how plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant is it to God, to ſee his ſecret ones making hard ſhifts to get
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:136315:16"/>together to worſhip him! <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Oh my Dove that art in the Clefts of the Rocks, in the ſecret places of the Stairs; let me ſee thy Countenance, let me hear thy Voice; for ſweet is thy Voice, and thy Countenance is comely.</hi> What are theſe<note n="*" place="margin">Non in domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio ſed in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibulo verſatur, <hi>Brightman in loc.</hi>
                  </note> Clefts of Rocks, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret places of the Stairs, but thoſe ſecret retiring places, where the People of God get together in difficult times to ſeek their God? there they<note n="†" place="margin">Hoc eſt illud os totum op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletum lachri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, cujus aſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctutam in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifice delectatur Dcus; ibid.</note> poured out their ſouls together in broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted confeſſions of ſin. <hi>The Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hillary, were not to be ſought,</hi> in Tectis et exteriori Pompa, (i.e.) <hi>in Palla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and outward Pomp, but rather in Deſerts and Mountains, in Dens and Caves of the Earth;</hi> as Heb. 11.38. <hi>In Queen</hi> Maries <hi>time,</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Fox</hi>) <hi>there were ſometimes</hi> 40,<note place="margin">Acts &amp; Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fol. <hi>1881.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſometimes an</hi> 100, <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times</hi> 200, <hi>came together as they could, in private places in</hi> London, <hi>for mutual edification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though men call this by hard names, and load it with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, as if it were Faction and Sedition, yet it undergoes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cenſure in Heaven. I remember<note n="*" place="margin">Cum boni, cum probi coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, non eſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio dicenda, ſed Curia, &amp; e contrario, illis nomen factionis accomino dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt, qui in odium bonorum et proborum conſpirant. <hi>Ter. Apol. cap. 39.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian,</hi> about 1400 years agoe, in his Apology, vindicates this Practice of theirs, againſt the Calumnies of the Heathen; <hi>When good Men meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it is not to be called a faction, but a Court. And on the contrary, the name of Faction is to be applied to them, who conſpire in hatred againſt good &amp; honeſt men. And what place is accounted ſo hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ourable, and abounds with delights, as the Courts of Princes?</hi> Yea, let us hear what a<note n="†" place="margin">Quaevis col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectio fidelium, eatiam ſi ob paucitatem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am intra, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatae domus parietis inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di poſſit, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amſi ob furo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem hoſtium nocturnos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventus agant, eſt vera eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia. <hi>Dav. in Loc. p. 410.</hi>
                  </note> Biſhop of our own ſpeaks of ſuch Meetings; <hi>Sometimes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the rage of Perſecution ſuffers not the Church to meet in the publick ſight of all, but forces them as it were, to creep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to private Holes;</hi> as Rev. 12.6. as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and other Orthodox Chriſtians, were fain to ſeek hiding places from the <hi>Arrians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Every Meeting of the Faithful, although for their fewneſs, they may be included within the walls of a Private Houſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by the fury of the Enemies, they keep their meeting by night, yet it is a true Church. Thus Biſhop <hi>Davenant.</hi> And truly if the Saints had nothing elſe but the gracious Preſence of Chriſt, (which is by promiſe engaged to be among them) it were enough to oppoſe to all the difficulties and dangers attending on ſuch a Duty. What a ſweet Promiſe is that, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.20. <hi>Where two or three are gathered together in my Name, there am I in the midſt of them: That is?</hi> ſaith <hi>Cameron, not only with them, but as a Preſident among them:</hi> Chriſt will be there to defend, teach and bleſs them. How often hath this Promiſe been made good to the experiences of the Saints? <hi>John</hi> 20.19. <hi>Then the ſame day at evening, being
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:136315:16"/>the firſt day of the week, when the doors were ſhut, where the Diſciples were aſſembled, for fear of the Jews, came Jeſus and ſtood in the midſt of them, and ſaith unto them, Peace be unto you.</hi> Oh if Jeſus be in the midſt of you, no matter how many Enemies combine againſt you; If He ſpeak peace to you, no matter who prepares war againſt you: 'tis worth the venturing far, to meet with Jeſus Chriſt, and enjoy fellowſhip with him in ſuch duties.</p>
               <p>And beſides, this is the way to prevent the decay and cooling of thy affections: In times of abounding iniquity, the love of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny will wax cold, <hi>but he that endureth to the end, the ſame ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Lo it is but an <hi>[He]</hi> (ſaith one upon the Text) a ſingle man, a very few, that hold out in compariſon of the Apoſtates. The whole world went wandring after the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.3, 4. Such was the paucity and obſcurity of Chriſtians in the <hi>Arrian</hi> Times, that <hi>Baſil</hi> cryes out, <hi>An Eccleſias ſuas proſus dereliquit Dominus?</hi> Hath the Lord utterly forfaken his Churches? the ſhip of the Church was then almoſt overwhelmed, faith <hi>Hierom;</hi> when the ſtorm is at its height, thou ſhalt ſee Profeſſors fal like the leaves in Autumne, or as rotten fruit in a windy day. The Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons Tail ſhall ſweep down the third part of the Stars. Now to fix thee in ſuch a day, the Communion of Saints is of ſingular uſe, they do wedge in and faſten one another; all the enemies rage could not ſever them; in the Primitive times, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.23. being let go, they went to their company:<note n="*" place="margin">In Spiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li ſocietate, hoc etiam locum precipue habet, ut matacis co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortationibus animorum in pietat frigus &amp; Congelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem inducto Deizelore pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus. <hi>Cartwright in Loc.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Two</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>are better than one, becauſe they have a good reward for their labour, for if they fall, the one will help up his fellow: But woe to him that is alone,</hi> Eccleſ. 4.9, 10. <hi>If two lye together, then they have heat; but how can one be warm alone?</hi> Communion with ſpiritual Chriſtians, affords this double benefit; if one ſtumble, yea fall, another will recover him; if ones affections grow chil, anothers zeal will warm them again: the benefit of ſuch Society, is unſpeakable: and truly the nearer you keep to God, the cloſer you will cleave to one another, as lines are nearer at the center.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="counsel">
               <head>COUNSEL <hi>V.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Study to keep your ſelves pure from the Corruptions of the preſent World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not only a great ſin, but an ill ſign, to be carried away with the ſtreams of the times. A Sin, becauſe directly oppoſite to the Command, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Be not conformed to this World,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,] to this age; the meaning is, do not get into the garb of the Times. And an ill Sign, becauſe the Scripture makes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:136315:17"/>it the character of a wicked man, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. <hi>They walk according to the courſe of this World.</hi> In the original [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] accord to the age, as the manner of the Times went: it is as dangerous living in ill company, as breathing in an infectious air; for as<note n="*" place="margin">Peccatum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo facile alios invadit, ut nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Peſtis tanto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere aerem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficere poteſt. <hi>Chem. Har.</hi>
                  </note> one obſerves well, <hi>No Pest doth ſooner infect the air, than Sin infects and defiles the mind:</hi> it is as hard a matter to preſerve your ſelvs from guilt among wicked men, as it is to keep your ſelves clean, where many dirty dogs are leaping and fawning upon you: the diſeaſes of the ſoul are very catching. How great a commendation was it to <hi>Noah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nemo erat ſibi ipſi, ſed demon tiam ſpargit in proximos. <hi>Seneca.</hi>
                  </note> that he was upright, and walked with God, when all fleſh had corrupted their wayes! And how beautiful a ſight is it to ſee Chriſtians ſhine as Lights in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe generation! <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. to continue a Lilly among Thorns, The world is a Sea, and every particular perſon in it a drop; now to ſee a drop of water in the Sea carried in a counter motion to the Tyde, is marvellous. Chriſtians are a diſtinct company of themſelves, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.23. <hi>You are of another world, Joh</hi> 17.14. and your converſes ſhould be in Heaven, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1, 2. and with Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Spirits, <hi>Pſal</hi> 16.3. Oh how hard is it to eſcape partnerſhip with them in ſin, if we converſe unneceſſarily among them! If fine bread be in the ſame Oven with courſe, the finer partakes of that which is courſe, but the courſe ſeldom partakes of the fine: If you lay bright and cleane Armour among that which is ruſty, the ruſty Armour communicates its ruſt to the clean, but the bright communicates not its brightneſs to the ruſty. There are more wayes than one, by which thou mayeſt be involved into guilt by them. Suppoſe thou conſenteſt not with them, muchleſs inſtigateſt them to ſin, yet mayeſt thou be defiled by their ſin, if it be but by thy ſilence when thou oughteſt to reprove them, <hi>Lev.</hi> 5.1. or by not being ſo grieved, and tenderly affected with their ſins, as thou oughteſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, 2. Thus did <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119.136. And <hi>Lot,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7, 8. that they might free their own ſouls. From this I might diſwade you by many Arguments: As,</p>
               <p>The expreſs command of God laid upon you;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> he hath forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den you to follow a<note n="*" place="margin">It may ſignifie ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> or <hi>diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam;</hi> either <hi>magnitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi> or <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem.</hi>
                  </note> multitude to do evil, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.2. it may be underſtood either of multitude or magnitude. Many men, or great men (for the will of God is not revealed to men with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect either to their numbers, or greatneſs; but his ſecret is with them that fear him;) to go in the way of evil men, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.14. to have no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works of darkneſs, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11. to ſave your ſelves from this untoward generation, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.40.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:136315:17"/>with many of like importance. And this is reaſon enough to make you cautelous, ſeeing God hath given ſuch expreſs prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in this caſe.</p>
               <p>The ſpecial eye of favour which God hath alwayes caſt upon <hi>ſuch</hi> as have been upright in their generation,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 2.</note> and kept them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>pure</hi> from the corruptions of the times they lived in. <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> walked with God, when the earth was overſpread with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation of wickedneſs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9. and <hi>Noah</hi> is ſaved by the Lord when the Earth is overwhelmed with an inundation of water, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Lot</hi> his righteous foul is vexed with the filthy conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> and he is graciouſly exempted from the deſolation that came upon them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.16. he would not joyn hands with ſinners, and God will take him by the hand, as a friend to reſcue him out of the danger. <hi>Elijah</hi> will walk with and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear for God, when he could ſee none to ſtand by him, when Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry had over-ſpread the face of the whole Country; and what miraculous and wonderful Providences did he experience in his protections and ſuſtentations! Either the Lord will hide him in the grave, from the troubles that ſhall be among the living, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.1. (ſo <hi>Anguſtin</hi> was taken away a little before the Sacking of <hi>Hyppo; Pareus</hi> a little before the taking of <hi>Heydelburg; Luther</hi> before the Wars break forth in <hi>Germany; Methuſela</hi> juſt before the Flood) or elſe he ſets ſome ſpecial mark upon them, that they may be diſtinguiſht in the general calamity, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.4, 5. <hi>Go through the midſt of Jeruſalem, and ſet a mark upon the foreheads of them that ſigh, and that cry for all the Abominatins that be done in the midſt thereof.</hi> And to the other he ſaid, <hi>Go after him, and ſmite, let not your eye ſpare, neither have ye pitty.</hi> So <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. before the Vials come to be poured out upon the Earth, the Servants of God are ſealed; even ſuch as had kept themſelves pure from An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Polutions.</p>
               <p>The danger we run our ſelves into thereby, dangers I ſay,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 3.</note> not only of deſtruction (Sor <hi>a companion of Fools ſhall be deſtroyed,</hi> Prov. 13.20.) but of defilement alſo; the Devil hath his Agents and Factors in every corner, to entice you to ſin, and you have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt hearts, as apt to receive impreſſions from the examples and perſwaſions of ſinners, as tinder is to receive fire; and it is no wiſdom you know, for him that carries Gunpowder about him, to come too near the fire, where the ſparks flie.</p>
               <p>Now to prevent this danger of being infected with the Sins and Evils of the Time, I ſhall lay down a few Directions.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:136315:18"/>
               <p n="1">1. If you would prevent Infection in theſe evil dayes, begin every day with God; ſeaſon your hearts ever morning by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Lord. This was <hi>Davids</hi> practice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.18. <hi>When I awake, I am ſtill with thee.</hi> It was bleſſed Counſel which a worthy perſon gives in this caſe; <hi>Before earthly things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>break in upon us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>T. Caſe</hi> in Epiſtle to the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</note> 
                  <hi>and we receive impreſſions from abroad, 'tis good to ſeaſon the heart with thoughts of God, and to conſecrate the early and virgin operations of the mind, before they are proſtituted to baſer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. When the World gets the ſtart of Religion in the morning, it can hardly overtake it all the day; and ſo the heart is habituated to vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty all the day long: but when we begin with God, we take him along with us to all the buſineſſes and comforts of the day; which being ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with his Love and Fear, are the more ſweet and ſavoury to us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Be choice in your company. Chriſt indeed converſed fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently with Publicans and Sinners, but it was ſtill in order to their good, and there was no danger of receiving any evil from them, there was nothing in him to faſten a temptation upon; but we can ſeldom get off without a taint.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Quicken up your zeal for God; this will be a ſpur to the diſcharge of your duty in all places, times and companies. <hi>Love</hi> (ſaid Mr. <hi>Gurnal</hi>) <hi>ever goes armed with Zeal, this is her dagger ſhe draws againſt all Oppoſers of Truth. Qui non zelat non amat.</hi> Many times we hear the Name of God prophan'd, and dare not take as much liberty and boldneſs to reprove ſin, as they do to commit it; whence is this but from the want of Zeal? O it would make thee, as it did <hi>Jonathan,</hi> to caſt a Kingdom at thy heels, to appear againſt Sin: and me-thinks thy intereſt in God, ſhould provoke thy zeal. We muſt not neglect the duty of a friend, for fear of incurring the ſuſpition of an enemy: 'tis better loſe the ſmiles than the ſouls of men: if thou diſcharge thy duty, the ſin is his; if not, 'tis thine too.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Furniſh your hearts with ſuch Principles, as are antidotes and preſervatives againſt infections. As Phyſicians adviſe in times of infection, to carry ſome Preſervatives ſtill about you. Of this ſort I ſhall commend four or five, and ſhut up this Head.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Nothing muſt lie nearer thy heart, if thou be a Chriſtian, than the Glory of thy God; all ends, intereſts &amp; deſigns, muſt be ſubjected to that; and whatſoever cannot be ſubordinated, muſt be rejected. If this Principle were but well ſetled upon the heart, what brave Spirits would it breed and raiſe in thy breaſt! it would untye thy tongue, like <hi>Craeſus</hi> his dumb ſon, to plead for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:136315:18"/>thy Father. It was a brave Speech of <hi>Hierom,</hi> in an evil day, when the rage of the enemy was great againſt the Name and People of God; <hi>O that they would turn their weapons upon me, and be ſatisfied with my Blood.</hi> And a ſweet one is that of <hi>Bernard</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Malo in nos murmur hominum, quam in Deum;</hi> Rather let their reproach fall on Us, than on God. <hi>Bonum eſt mihi ſi dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitur Deus, me uti pro Clypeo;</hi> I ſhould account it a mercy, if God would vouchſaſe to uſe me as a Shield. Much like that of <hi>David, The Reproaches of them that reproached thee, are fallen on me.</hi> If Gods Glory be thy principal end, thus it will ſubject all other ends and intereſts to it, and then it will open thy mouth to plead for him, and appear in all the concernments of his Name.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Peace of thine own Conſcience. is to be preferred to the favour of any man, and will abundantly recompence the frowns of men. <hi>This is our rejoycing, even the Teſtimony of our Conſcience.</hi> This is the ſweeteſt friends, ſacrifice it not to any mans luſt or will.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The greateſt expreſſion of love to another, is to hate his ſin. Prov. 27.6. <hi>Faithful are the Wounds of a Friend;</hi> and the greateſt injury to another, is to connive at his wickedneſs, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17.</p>
               <p n="4">4. No man ſhall be a loſer at laſt, by being faithful to God, and to his Duty; if you have no reward from men, yet to be ſure you ſhall from God; and yet God ſo orders it oftentimes, that men ſhall love you the better for your Faithfulneſs; Prov. 28.23. <hi>He that rebukes a man, afterwards ſhall find more favour than he that flatters with his lips.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. A Chriſtian ſhould do that, and nothing but that now, which he judges will be comfortable to him in a calm review at death and judgement: this would make you accurate Chriſtians indeed. O treaſure up theſe Principles, and live in the daily exerciſe of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="counsel">
               <head>COUNSEL VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prepare for fiery Tryals, whilſt the Lord gives you ſuch a gracious Seaſon of Peace and Liberty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eccleſ. 8.5. <hi>A wiſe mans heart diſcerneth both Time and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And indeed it is a ſpecial point of wiſdom, to apprehend and improve Seaſons aright. Chriſtian, thou muſt uſe thy forſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faculties, to diſcover dangers at a<note n="*" place="margin">Non facile inveniuntur praeſidia in adverſitat, quae non fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint in pace Queſitae. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> diſtance, and ſo prevent ſurprizals; <hi>A prudent man fore ſeeth the evil,</hi> Prov. 22.3. yea, ſenſe it ſelf teacheth the bruit Beaſts to get to the hedge, when a ſtorm is coming; and canſt not thou forſee a Storm in the Clouds, do
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:136315:19"/>they not gather blacker and blacker over thy head? O prepare for it; get thy ſuffering Graces, thy winter Germents on. <hi>Put them in mind</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>to be ready to every good Work,</hi> Tit. 3.1. be it active or paſſive obedience, you muſt be ready for it. Bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi> had fitted and provided himſelf, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.13. <hi>I am [ready] not only to be bound, but to dye at Jeruſalem for the Name of the Lord Jeſus;</hi> he had, as I may ſay, laid his neck on the block before hand, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6. <hi>I am ready,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to be offered up.</hi> Thus Chriſt was ready for his ſufferings, <hi>Loe I come,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>upon the Fathers Call,</hi> Pſal. 40.7. And as this is an argument of an heart truly gracious, ſo is it a ſingular advantage to the Chriſtian when troubles come; it is as the ſhoe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.15. <hi>and your feet ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpel of Peace.</hi> Ah when you come off theſe plains of peace and liberty, into the hard rugged paths. of ſuffering, you will find what a benefit it will be to you, to be well ſhod with this preparation of the Goſpel of Peace. <hi>Habak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kuk</hi> had it. <hi>chap.</hi> 3.16. <hi>I trembled in my ſelf, that I might reſt in the day of trouble:</hi> and then when difficulties and ſtraits came, he could go away ſinging under them, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. <hi>Though the fig-tree,</hi> &amp;c. yea, he could walk ſecurely through the thickets of trouble, and over the craggy rocks and precipices of danger, as is intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>The Lord God is my ſtrength, and he will make my feet like Hinds feet, (i.e.)</hi> to paſs with eaſe, <hi>per montes, per rupta,</hi> in ſuch wayes of difficulty as would diſtract others: <hi>and he will ſet me. upon my high places; (i.e.)</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Libere et abſquae metu in cedere in locis excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis.</note> he will enable me to go without fear over Mountains of trouble. Oh Chriſtian, how ſoon a ſtorm may riſe thou knoweſt not, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.2. <hi>Acts</hi> 12.1. to be ſure it will not be long, the Heavens are black, and ſome drops already fallen: prepare therefore for it, and have your ſuffering Graces ready.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But what are they? and how muſt they be prepared?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> Though every Grace is neceſſary in its place, and in the courſe of a Chriſtians converſation, comes to take his turn; as every ſpoak in a wheel bears a ſtreſs, and is of uſe in the whole turn and round thereof; yet as thoſe ſpoaks which are undermoſt at preſent, do preſent ſervice, ſo thoſe Graces which are now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, and are to bear the preſent burden of this day, are ſuch as theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Faith.</hi> This hath a precedency given in to all other Graces; as in point of juſtification, ſo of ſuſtentation in a ſuffering hour; <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Above all, taking the ſhield of Faith:</hi> this is like the liver-vein, this goes to Chriſt, and conveies Blood and Life to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:136315:19"/>the ſoul from him; now <hi>the Juſt ſhall live by Faith, Heb.</hi> 10.38. It was by Faith thoſe renowned Worthies, <hi>Heb</hi> 11. performed ſuch glorious Actions. By Faith it is that a poor Chriſtian gets a glimpſe of the inviſible God, and Glory, which marvellouſly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports him under diſtreſſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.27. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18. By this the ſoul is filled with peace and inward tranquility, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 2. And that is a ſingular preparation for ſuffering, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.15. <hi>Smite Lord, ſmite</hi> (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi>) <hi>for my ſins are forgiven me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Feri Domine feri, nam a peccatis meis abſolutus ſum. <hi>Luth.</hi>
                  </note> By Faith a poor ſoul rouls its ſelf and its burden upon God, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. and ſo quits and diſcharges it ſelf of all that anxiety and perplexity of ſpirit, which puts the ſinking weight into affliction. Oh then look to thy Faith, ſee it be not only alive, but <hi>lively;</hi> keep that Grace in thy heart, and thou ſhalt do well.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Patience;</hi> a Grace fitted for the purpoſe: it is not only a grace it ſelf, but the Conſervatory of other graces. And God hath placed Temperance on the right hand of Godlineſs, to defend it from injury by the flatteries and allurements of the world, ſo hath he placed Patience on the left, to defend it from the wrong it might receive by adverſity, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6. a grace ſo neceſſary in an evil day, that the Spirit hath ſet it in equipage with Faith it ſelf, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.12. and the Crown promiſed to it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. 'Tis an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Grace, bred by tribulation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3. will make a Chriſtian long-winded in his race to Glory. Oh then beg that you may be ſtrengthened with all might in the Inner-man, unto all Patience; if not, though you may be ſet out with much ſeeming gallantry of reſolution, yet you muſt needs faint in the way, and fall ſhort at laſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Holy Courage</hi> and <hi>Magnanimity.</hi> This Grace muſt now ſay in thy heart, as <hi>Elijah</hi> once did; <hi>As the Lord lives I will ſhew my ſelf.</hi> How conſpicuous hath this Grace been in thoſe worthy He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro's that are paſt on before us. See <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>per tot. Acts</hi> 20.24. &amp; 21.13. When <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperour endeavoured to draw <hi>Baſil</hi> from the faith, he firſt offers him great preferments, but his ſpirit was raiſed above that; <hi>Offer theſe things</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>to Children:</hi> then he tryes him by threanings of grievous torments, but his ſpirit was above that alſo; <hi>Threaten theſe things</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>to your purple Gallants, that give themſelves to pleaſure.</hi> The ſame <hi>Baſil</hi> relates the anſwer of the fourty Martyrs (whoſe ſtory he writes) When the Perſecutors, ſaith he, offered them great Preferments to draw them from Chriſt, this was their anſwer; <hi>Why offer you to us theſe ſmall things of the world, when you know the whole world is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:136315:20"/>by us?</hi> One of the Nobles of <hi>Jutian</hi> preſent at the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting of <hi>Marcus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Aerthuſa,</hi> was forced to ſay, <hi>We are aſhamed,</hi> O Emperor, <hi>the Chriſtians laugh at your Cruelty, and grow the more reſolute. Our very Women and Children, not to ſpeak of men</hi> (ſaith <hi>Lactantius</hi>) <hi>do overcome their Tormentors, and the fire cannot fetch ſo much as a ſigh from them.</hi> The ſame glorious Spirit of courage for the Lord Jeſus, reſted alſo upon <hi>Luther,</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Quas non oportet mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes praeelige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, quod non ſupplicium potius ferre, imo in quam profundam inferni abyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inferni abyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trare, quam contra con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam atteſtari. <hi>Zuing 3 Epiſt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius,</hi> and thoſe bleſſed Souls that freely offered themſelves to the Lord in <hi>Qucen Maryes</hi> time. And truly Chriſtian, not only ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity which lies upon thee, ſhould provoke courage, for there is no retreating, unleſs thou reſolve to periſh, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. but me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks the infinite Excellency of Chriſt, in whoſe Cauſe &amp; Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel thou art engaged, exacts it of thee, and ſhould make thee lay down all at his feet, not by conſtraint, but willingly, looking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as thy priviledge, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Laſtly, to name no more, <hi>Self-denial</hi> muſt now be promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; <hi>If any man will come after me, he muſt deny himſelf, Mark,</hi> 8.34. both ſinful ſelf, which muſt abſolutely and univerſally be denyed; and <hi>natural,</hi> yea <hi>religious</hi> Self, which muſt reſpectively and in ſome caſes be denyed alſo. The want of this, hath been the down-fall and ruine of many an eminent Profeſſor. The moſt dangerous nick and opportunity of temptation, is when a man is tryed in his darling luſt; now he falls by the root, if that be not mortified. This was the ruine of <hi>Judas;</hi> Covetouſneſs was his predominant luſt; and when he was tryed there, he falls imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.16. <hi>What will you give me, and I will betray him?</hi> This overturned <hi>Demas</hi> alſo. Oh conſider theſe things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="counsel">
               <head>COUNSEL VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Get your hearts deeply affected with Sions Miſery, and ſtrive ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly with the Lord on its behalf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.5. <hi>If I forget thee, O Jeruſalem, let my tongue eleave to the roof of my mouth.</hi> The pouring out of this Spirit of compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will be a token for good to us: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.13. <hi>Thou wilt ariſe and have mercy upon Sion, for the time to favour her, yea the ſet-time is come:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Caſe</hi> in <hi>Englands</hi> Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; p. 74.</note> But how knew he that? <hi>for thy Servants take pleaſure in her ſtones, and favour the duſt thereof.</hi> Upon which words one gloſſeth thus; <q rend="inline">It is as if he ſhould ſay, would you have me give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of my hope and confidence, that God will ariſe and have mercy upon Sion; why (ſaith he) do you not ſee the Servants
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:136315:20"/>of God every where troubled for Sion, and bemoan Sion, and weep over her, crying out over her ruines, <hi>O is this Sion?</hi> what, the City of our Solemnities? what, ſhe that was the praiſe and beauty of the whole Earth? Ah Lord, who can hold his peace at ſuch a ſight as this? Oh who can look upon Sion with dry eyes? are theſe her ſtones that lye thus ſcattered in the duſt? Oh it is a thouſand pitties to ſee Sion in ſuch a ſad and mournful condition? Oh that our head were waters, and our eyes rivers of tears! Come Sirs, what ſhall we do for Sion? is there nothing we can do by our counſels, our prayers for the repairing of theſe breaches?</q> Oh thus it ſhould be with us at this day: <hi>Non ſunt iſta litigandi ſed orandi tempora,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> ſaid of his day, Theſe are not times of ſtriving, but praying; it's no time now to ſtrive with one another, but to unite our ſtrength, and like the true generation of <hi>Jacob,</hi> to be ſtriving with our God. To be minding the world, and ſeeking of great things for our ſelves now, is no ſmall evil: God expects his Saints ſhould now be cloathed in Black, and walk as true Mourners un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the great and ſore rebukes of their Father: ſhould we now make mirth? <hi>Ezck.</hi> 21.10. <hi>It contemneth the rod of my Son, as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tree.</hi> God brings it in as an heavy charge upon the People, <hi>Amos</hi> 6.6. that they are not grieved for the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph;</hi> or as the Hebrew, over the rentings and tearnings in pieces of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> that is, the Church. It is a lively Alluſion to the ſad Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that old <hi>Jacob</hi> made over the ſuppoſed renting of his dear <hi>Joſeph, Gen.</hi> 42.21. <hi>Joſeph is not,</hi> I will go down to the grave to my Son mourning: but his Brethren ſaw the anguiſh of his ſoul, and pittied him not. And may not many of the Lords own Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, charge the ſame thing upon their hearts at this day, that they did upon themſelves, <hi>We are verily guilty</hi> (ſay they) <hi>concerning our Brother Joſeph.</hi> Ah! have we not heard of the anguiſh of Sion, and the ſore diſtreſs upon many of her Children at this day, and yet have not been ſo tenderly touch'd with the due ſenſe of it? Oh write that man bowelleſs, that hath no compaſſion in his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit now for Sion: you may promiſe to your ſelf immunity from the common calamity, but God hath ſaid, <hi>Amos</hi> 6.7. <hi>You ſhall go captive with the firſt that go captive.</hi> Ah! is this a time, as God ſaid to <hi>Baruk, Jer.</hi> 45. to ſeek great things for your ſelves, it is enough if you have your life for a prey: are you now build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and feathering your nerts, when the Axe of Judgement lyes at the root of that tree you build in, to cut it down? Surely we
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:136315:21"/>may ſay of ſuch deſigns now, as <hi>Huſhai</hi> did of the counſel of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel, It is not good at this time.</hi> In that day did the Lord call to mourning; and is there not as loud a Call at this day? <hi>The Voice of the Rod cryeth to to the City, Micha</hi> 6.9. Oh he not deaf to that Cry: now go to the Lord with an holy importunity, under a quick ſenſe of Sions miſery, and give him no reſt till he ariſe and have mercy on her. And among many other, there Arguments may perſwade to it.</p>
               <p>The gracious Nature of that God to whom you go for help and mercy;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 1.</note> Oh remember you lye down at the feet of a tender-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Father, willing to be overcome by you: <hi>Amos</hi> 4.12. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thus will I do unto thee, and becauſe I will do thus, prepare to meet thy God, O Iſrael, (i.e.)</hi> in a way of humiliation to prevent him: So <hi>Luke</hi> 18.7. And ſhall not God avenge his <hi>[own Elect]</hi> that cry unto him day and night, though he bear long with them? mark the motive <hi>[his own;] q.d.</hi> Can a Father ſhut up the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of mercy from his own fleſh? how much leſs God, to whoſe compaſſions, the moſt dear and tender affections of all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in the world, is but as a drop to the Ocean. This <hi>Jonah</hi> well underſtood, <hi>Jonah</hi> 4.2. <hi>Was not this my ſaying when I was yet in my Country, therefore I fled before unto</hi> Tarſhiſh, <hi>for I knew that thou art a gracious God, ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſs, and repenteſt thee of the evil; q.d.</hi> yea Lord, I knew before-hand what it would come to; I muſt go to <hi>Niniveh,</hi> and denounce thy Judgements againſ it, and then if they do but humble themſelves a little, thy Mercies and Compaſſions are ſo tender and abundant, that thou canſt not ſmite them; if they do but come upon the knee, the rod falls out of thy hand; I knew it would be ſo, I was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded before hand, that Free-Grace would make me appear as a lyar to them, therefore I fled to <hi>Tarſhiſh.</hi> Oh what a Motive is this, to bring you upon the knee before God at this day!</p>
               <p>Conſider how dear an Intereſt it is that you eſpouſe and plead for,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 2.</note> dear to God, and therefore the greater probability of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; you may ſay to God, as <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Martha</hi> did to Chriſt concerning their brother <hi>Lazarus, Lord, he whom thou loveſt is ſick.</hi> Ah the Intereſt of his Son, which I perſwade you to plead with him, lyes near his heart; and dear to you, if you be real Saints: for alas, what joy can you have to ſurvive Sions proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity? would you not in ſuch a caſe ſay as the Prophet, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.4. <hi>Ah Lord God, it is enough, take away my life alſo.</hi> O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtrive with God for it.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:136315:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Conſider how much you have contributed to the provoking and procuring cauſe of its preſent miſery;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 3.</note> 'tis Sions own Sons and Daughters that have procured this unto her; and ſhall there be none among all the Sons ſhe hath brought up to take her by the hand, and comfort her? 'tis our conteſts and wrangling one with another, our barrenneſs under the Goſpel, our abuſe of Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, and moſt precious Goſpel-Enjoyments, that have procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all this: Ah Sirs! will you not ſtrive to pray back the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, you have helped to ſin away?</p>
               <p>Thoſe that are moſt deeply humbled,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Arg. 4.</note> and do moſt fervently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercede for Sion now, ſhall have a peculiar ſhare in her Joy when the Lord reſtores it: <hi>When the Lord turned again the Captivity of Sion, we were like them that dream'd, then was our mouth filled with laughter, and our tongue with ſinging,</hi> Pſal. 126.1, 2. But who were theſe that laugh and rejoyce at Sions mercy? were they not ſuch as had mourned for her; yes, yes, they that thus reap in joy, are ſuch as had before ſown in tears, <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 6. to ſuch indeed the Promiſe is mader, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.18. &amp; 66.10. Rejoyce for joy with her, all ye that mourn for her. Let theſe things affect your ſouls.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="counsel">
               <head>COUNSEL <hi>VIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>* <hi>That ſeeing a Day of great trouble is approaching, and all outward comforts ready to take their farewel of you, you would now give all diligence to clear up your title to Chriſt, and intereſt in that Kingdom that cannot be ſhaken.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>If ever we had need to make all honeſt haſte to Heaven, and to clear up our intereſt in it, this is the time; what have we beſides this to oppoſe to all our troubles here? what will you do when all earthly comforts are fled? and are they not upon the wing? when it comes to reſiſting to blood, and giving up all, can you fadge with ſuch work as this, while your ſpirits are dubious and cloudy in this point? O my friends believe it, its nothing but this that can make a Saint triumph &amp; glory in Abaſures and Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16, 17, 18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3. And little do you imagin how inſupportable troubles are, when the ſpirit is low and dubious in point of intereſt. The Devil, like a true coward, falls upon a poor Saint, when he is proſtrate in his ſpirit, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der trouble, then he pours in diſcouragements from all hands; he loves to fall upon them, as <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> did upon the <hi>Shechemites</hi> when they were ſore, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.25. Satan knowes men
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:136315:22"/>will hardly part with their preſent ſenſible comforts, till they be aſſured of better: It's eaſier without doubt, for an aſſured Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to lay down his neck for Chriſt, than for another to part with a piece of his eſtate, or bear a reproach for him: and truly whether we conſult ſafety or comfort, whether we conſider the ineffable ſweetneſs of that Peace and Joy begotten by aſſurance; or the Miſery of being ſubjected in a day of trouble to the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings, doubts and fears of a perplexed ſpirit, you will find that all theſe conſiderations do put a neceſſity, a ſollemnity, a glory upon this work: But oh the difficulties and dangers attending it! what judgement, faithfulneſs, reſolution, watchfulneſs doth it require! ſuch is the darkneſs, deceitfulneſs, inconſtancy of the heart; and ſuch the malice, pollicy, and diligence of Satan to improve it, that he who attempts this work, and need both to watch his ſeaſons for it, frequently to look up to God for gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and illumination; and to ſpend many ſad and ſerious thoughts before he determine this buſineſs.</p>
                  <p>To the end therefore, that this moſt weighty and important Work may not miſcarry in thy hands, I intreat thee carefully to obſerve theſe ſix Dirextions following.</p>
                  <p>Be ſure thou try thy ſelf by ſound and approved Marks of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity,<note place="margin">Direction <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> and not by ſuch as are only probable and common to hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, for theſe will fail when any ſtreſs is laid upon them, and like the Reeds of <hi>Egypt,</hi> pierce into thine hand.</p>
                  <p>To help thee herein, I have collected the beſt Scripture-Marks illuſtrated and prepar'd for thy uſe, by the labours of ſome of our moſt skilful Heart-Anatomiſts. The ſubſtance of which I ſhall here tranſcribe, leſt you ſhould not have the books at hand.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Four Signs of a ſincere Heart, by Mr. <hi>Gurnal,</hi> in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of his Treatiſe on <hi>Epheſ. 6. p. 127, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1ſt. <hi>Mark.</hi> A ſincere heart, is a <hi>new heart, Ezek.</hi> 11.19. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it was formerly divided among the creatures, now it is gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into God: it hath but one deſign, which above all it purſues; and that is to approve it ſelf to God; As one that having many pieces of old ſilver lying by him, which he intends to put into one bowl; he firſt reſolves to caſt it a new, and to that end throwes it into the fire to melt, and ſo at laſt ſhuts up all in one piece.</p>
                  <p n="2">2d. <hi>Mark.</hi> A ſincere heart, is a <hi>ſimple plain heart;</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:136315:22"/>and this Simplicity appears in three things. (1.) In ranſacking it ſelf, in which it is exceeding diligent, and fearful of a miſtake, willing to know the worſt of himſelf; in judging it ſelf, when the ſin is found, he proceeds to ſentance a luſt, as well as to ſearch diligently for it. (2.) In plain dealing with God as well as with it ſelf: An hypocrite asks what he would not thank God to give him, but a ſincere ſoul is deeply affected, when his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are not anſwered, and uſes the means to obtain his deſires. (3.) In plain dealing with men, he will not ſubject his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to fleſhly intereſts, nor ſhape his courſe to the times.</p>
                  <p n="3">3d. <hi>Mark.</hi> The ſincere Chriſtian is <hi>uniform;</hi> and that (1.) As to the object; (2.) The ſubject; (3.) The circumſtances of his obedience. For the firſt, his heart lies cloſe to the whole Law of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.11. hath reſpect to all the Commands: as for the ſubject, the whole man (ſo far as renewed) moves one way; judgement, will, affections, move uniformly: as to circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, he is holy in all times, places, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="4">4th. <hi>Mark.</hi> The ſincere Chriſtian, is <hi>progreſſive,</hi> is not content with any meaſure of Grace, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13, 15. never at his journies end, till he get to Heaven, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Five Marks of Uprightneſs, by Mr. <hi>Obadiah Sedgwick,</hi> in his Anatomy of Uprightneſs, <hi>p. 202, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1ſt. <hi>Mark.</hi> If a man be upright, he will moſtly ſtrive for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reformation of his heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.10. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.9. it is not ſufficient his outward actions look well, unleſs his heart were better: Oh, ſaith he, that this heart were better, more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, more humble, more believing: the principal regard of the hypocrite is to externals.</p>
                  <p n="2">2d. <hi>Mark.</hi> If a man be upright, a little holineſs will not ſerve his turn, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12, 13, 14, 15.</p>
                  <p n="3">3d. <hi>Mark.</hi> A perſon may know his uprightneſs by the conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable diſpoſition of his heart about all ſins, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.23. <hi>Job</hi> 1.1. Hypocrites have ſtill ſome way of wickedneſs. Such a ſoul as is upright, will make conſcience of ſecret as well as open ſins, <hi>Job</hi> 31.26, 27, &amp;c. <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.5. yea, of the leaſt ſins. <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſomote him for cutting off the skirt of <hi>Sauls</hi> garment: yea, of ſins, which are in a ſort more connatural to him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.23. In a word, Uprightneſs appears in nine things about ſins. (1.) It will endure Tryal, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.23. (2.) It will often try it
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:136315:23"/>ſelf. (3.) It ſcares it ſelf, and is ſuſpicious. (4.) It will bleſs God for being kept from ſin; as <hi>David</hi> did for <hi>Abigaels</hi> Counſel. (5.) It is more ſevere againſt its own ſins, than anothers. (6.) It condemns ſin in all; in Parents, as <hi>Jonathan</hi> in <hi>Saul:</hi> in Children, as <hi>Jacob</hi> in <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi:</hi> in great ones, as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> in <hi>Herod.</hi> (7.) It grieves for its own ſins, and the ſins of others alſo. Rivers of water ran down <hi>Davids</hi> eyes upon that account. (8.) It's more moved for ſins againſt God, than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries done to it ſelf: As <hi>David</hi> cannot bear <hi>Goliahs</hi> Blaſphemies, yet can bear <hi>Shimeis</hi> railings. (9.) Abſtinence ſufficeth not without hatred; and hatred ſufficeth not without mortification.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Mark</hi> Uprightneſs is known by a mans diſpoſition about holy Duties. And in holy Duties, five things manifeſt the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs of the heart.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Univerſality. Pſal.</hi> 119.6. <hi>Acts</hi> 24.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.18. An hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite's obedience cannot be univerſal, becauſe his grounds and motives are but particular.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By its <hi>conſtancy, Job</hi> 2.3. ſtill he holdeth faſt his intregity. There are three times in which an hypocrite may expreſs great forwardneſs; (1.) When ſtraits of conſcience are on him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.16. (2.) When duties are not dangerous, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.5, 6, 20. (3.) In the preſence of others; as <hi>Joaſh,</hi> while <hi>Jehojadah</hi> lived.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By <hi>ſimplicity</hi> of obedience, when a man looks not at him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but at God's Command, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. &amp; 5.14.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. By the <hi>ſpirituality</hi> of obedience, when the very heart and ſoul, the ſpirit and affections act themſelves, and co-operate with our ſervices, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.5, 6.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. by the <hi>humility</hi> of obedience. Hypocrites are proud of their work. When God enlarges the heart, a Saint may rejoyce; but the Hypocrite will boaſt. A Saint gives all to God, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.13, 14.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Mark.</hi> A fifth tryal of Uprightneſs is, if the bent and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the heart be unto God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.8. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.31. <hi>Acts</hi> 11.23. and this bent or purpoſe of the heart, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies three things. (1.) An inward deſire, joyned with love, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.5. (2.) An habitual inclination, not a ſuddain pang, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.20. (3.) An active purpoſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Six Tryals of Sincerity, ſuch as no hypocrite in the world can have; By Mr. <hi>Sydenham,</hi> in his Treatiſe of Hypocriſie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tryal</hi> 1. To hate ſin as ſin, to hate it in its whole nature, in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:136315:23"/>its firſt motions, not becauſe it troubles the conſcience, or brings me to hell, or renders me unſutable to my deſigns and relations in the world, but as it is ſin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tryal</hi> 2. No hypocrite can delight to be made aſhamed by God in its duties, to be made purely nothing in its own eyes, and the eyes of others. This a ſincere ſoul can do, he can take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the Lords humbling of him. An Hypocrite cannot endure to be outſhined; the principle that acts him, is ſelf-love: but a Saint loves to be laid low before God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tryal</hi> 3. No Hypocrite can bleſs God, and love him from his heart: when God ſmites him in his deaerſt enjoyments, or near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt luſts; ſtrike him in any thing that the eye or heart of him is upon, and he ſecretly hates Chriſt. Now a Saint in ſuch a caſe, will cling to Chriſt, he cannot but love him for all that.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tryal</hi> 4. No Hypocrite can love the perſon of Chriſt, nor a Saint, as a Saint; he only loves to be pardoned by him, and have ſome comfort from him; but never finds his heart to work in love to Chriſt, and have union with him, as the ground of all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts. And ſo, for a Saint, loves him not as ſuch, but as ſo and ſo tempered and qualified.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tryal</hi> 5. No Hypocrite can go on in any ſpiritual work or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for Chriſt with any contentment, without ſenſible comforts, or outward reſpects, the wind of men fill his ſails: But a Saint can take pleaſure in the pooreſt work of Chriſt, wherein he is leaſt ſeen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tryal</hi> 6. No Hypocrite in the world can long to be like Chriſt, as to be reſpected by Chriſt; he cannot love the Holineſs of Chriſt, as the good things he gets by Chriſt: But a ſincere heart, if he have never ſo much comfort, yet if he be not like Chriſt, is not pleaſed. — And this is the firſt Direction, try by ſound evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of ſincerity.</p>
                  <p>Make choice of the fitteſt ſeaſons for this great Work,<note place="margin">Direct. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> and ſet about this, when you find your hearts in the moſt quiet and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſt frame; for as he that will ſee his face in a glaſs, muſt be fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and not in motion; or in the water, muſt not diſturb or make any commotion in it; ſo is it in this caſe; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with your own heart upon your bed, and be ſtill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Endeavour to caſt out and watch againſt <hi>Self-love,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Direct. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> leſt thy heart being prepoſſeſt thereby, thy judgement be blinded, and become partial in paſſing ſentence upon thy eſtate: labour to bring thy heart to be willing to know the worſt of it ſelf; yea, and if thou
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:136315:24"/>have all this while been deceived, to bleſs the Lord, that now at laſt thy miſtake is diſcovered, and to be willing to lay the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation new again. This you muſt do, for he that will put on the perſon of a Judge, muſt put off the perſon of a friend.</p>
                  <p>Labour to keep upon thy heart a deep and lively ſence of the approaching Judgement,<note place="margin">Direct. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> throughout this work, knowing what a potent influence this hath upon the conſcience to make it delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, ſerious and faithful in its work; and therefore demand of thine own conſcience, upon the reſolution of each Queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it will own and ſtand to that it now ſpeaks in the great day, when the counſels of all hearts ſhall be made manifeſt.</p>
                  <p>Go to the Lord by prayer when thou art going about this work,<note place="margin">Direct. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> and earneſtly beg guidance and aſſiſtance from him therein: it is the work of the Spirit to ſeal and aſſure thee; and he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him to that purpoſe to ſuch as ſeek him, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. <hi>John</hi> 14.26.</p>
                  <p>Condemn not thy ſelf preſently for an Hypocrite,<note place="margin">Direct. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note> upon the diſcoveries of thy many weakneſſes and imperfections in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; theſe ſhould humble, but not diſcourage thee; it is not thine inevitable weakneſſes, thy ſenſible dullneſs, thy lamented roavings, thine oppoſed diſtractions, thy miſtaken unbelief (as one well notes) that argues thee Chriſtleſs, or excludes thee from the Promiſes, <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.27, 28, 29, 30. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.2. theſe break not the bond of the Covenant: the Lord expects not Angelical per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from you in this eſtate, but looks at your ſincerity, and knows, as a father, how to pitty your lamented infirmities, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.11, 12, 13, 14.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb facs="tcp:136315:24"/>
            <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
            <p>ANd now I have given you my beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and counſel to preſerve you from the ſnares and evils that are, and are coming upon the world; what uſe you will make of it, I know not. I doubt not but it will find a welcome reception among humble and hungry ſouls, though the full and wanton ſoul deſpiſe it. <hi>He that hearkeneth unto Counſel</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>is wiſe,</hi> Prov. 12.15. And if thy heart be ſhut by pride or intereſt againſt it, it is an omious ſign to thy ſoul, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.16. and preſages ruine. Which ſad event, I ſhall beg the Lord in Mercy to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
